<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reflections on a letter writ by a nameless author to the reverend clergy of both universities and on his bold reflections on the trinity &amp;c. / by Richard Frankland.</title>
            <author>Frankland, Richard, 1630-1698.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 140 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40396</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2077</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31715</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12247340</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12247340</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56998</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40396)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56998)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1504:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reflections on a letter writ by a nameless author to the reverend clergy of both universities and on his bold reflections on the trinity &amp;c. / by Richard Frankland.</title>
                  <author>Frankland, Richard, 1630-1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 54 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for A. &amp; J. Churchill, and sold by F. Bently ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College Library, Cambridge University.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Trinity.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56998:1"/>
            <p>REFLECTIONS ON A LETTER Writ by a NAMELESS AUTHOR TO THE <hi>Reverend Clergy of both Univerſities</hi>' And on his BOLD REFLECTIONS ON THE TRINITY, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Richard Frankland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>A.</hi> &amp; <hi>J. Churchill,</hi> and ſold by <hi>F. Bently</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Halifax,</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:56998:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56998:2"/>
            <head>A PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>EVER ſince the Divine Oracle ſounded the Alarum of War between the Seed of the Woman and Serpent's Brood, <hi>Gen. 3. 18.</hi> the Devil and his Agents have ſpit their Poyſon againſt our bleſſed Lord Jeſus, the Captain of our Salvation. For ſome Thouſands of Years the World was invelop'd in the Miſt of Ignorance: Heathen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm, Barbariſm, Scythiſm, and Helleniſm overſpread the Face of the Earth: And when the Goſpel-Sun appeared in our Horizon, the Heathen raged, Kings and Rulers raiſed all the Militia of Earth and Hell: And by the joint Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy of Jews and Gentiles, this Son of God was abuſed, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, crucified: And ſince his Reſurrection, by the Power of his God-head, and glorious Aſcenſion to the right Hand of the Majeſty on high, What a Number of Hereticks have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to pull him down from the Throne of his Glory, and degrade him of his Deity, the moſt orient Pearl in his Crown? Strange were the Figments of <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> and <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinians</hi> of old, the Followers of <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> who
<pb facs="tcp:56998:3"/> overturned Goſpel Revelations by their Aeones, Combinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Conjugations, Genealogies, and unintelligible Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. <hi>Cerinthus</hi> and <hi>Ebion</hi> in the firſt Century, affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that Chriſt was only a Man, begotten between <hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary: Cerdon</hi> and <hi>Marcion</hi> in the ſecond Century, denied the Verity of Chriſt's Humane Nature and Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: In the third Century, <hi>Theodoſian</hi> alſo denyed Chriſt's Divinity: <hi>Artemon</hi> ſaid Chriſt was not exiſtent before he took Fleſh of the Virgin: The <hi>Sabellians</hi> denyed the Three Perſons in the God head: Yes, they affirmed that the Father cloathed himſelf with our Nature, dyed, called therefore <hi>Patripaſſians: Samoſetanus</hi> alſo denyed Chriſt's Divinity: The <hi>Maniches</hi> held the ſame heretical Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, which did at laſt center in <hi>Arius,</hi> and ſpread through the World. <hi>A. D. 324.</hi> condemned by the Council of <hi>Nice: Neſtorius</hi> contradicted the Perſonal Union of the Divine and Humane Natures in Chriſt: <hi>Eutichus</hi> confounded theſe two Natures, ſaying, <hi>The Humane was ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up by the Immenſity of the Divine:</hi> The <hi>Agnoitae</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed the Perfection of Knowledge in the Divine Nature of Chriſt: Others called Chriſt only the adoptive Son of God: all theſe had their Followers: Yet God raiſed up learned Men to oppoſe and ſuppreſs theſe Hereticks in all Ages: Some of them came to aſtoniſhing Ends, by the juſt Judgment of God, and ſome by the Sentence of Men, as <hi>Servetus</hi> at <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva, A. D. 1652. Gorgius Blandrata, Petrus Stato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> vented pernicious Errours in <hi>Poland,</hi> but the later diſſembled, and was found in his Bed with his Neck bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: But the Errours ſettled in <hi>Fauſtus Socinus, A. D.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:56998:3"/> 1565. born at <hi>Sens:</hi> A witty Scholar got his Uncle <hi>Lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Socinus's</hi> Books, comes into <hi>Poland,</hi> writes a Book, <hi>De Jeſu Chriſto Servatore,</hi> at <hi>Cracovia,</hi> whereof he boaſted, and was anſwered by ſeveral, in a Diſputation: The Orthodox confounded the Anti-trinitarians from plain Scripture-Texts, and ancient Writers; ſo that Religion mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prevailed: But ſome falling off to Tritheiſm, Anabaptiſm, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they regarded not what Principles they owned, ſo they were but Enemies to the Doctrin of the Trinity.</p>
            <p>One thing is obſervable; ſeveral in that confuſed Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny denying Religious Worſhip to Chriſt, <hi>Socinus</hi> contended with them, but was ſilenced and bafled by his own Principles, who held that Chriſt was meer Man, therefore by conſequence it would be Idolatry to worſhip him: There were alſo ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Errours broach'd by <hi>Socinus,</hi> that the Condition of the firſt Man was Mortal, that there's no original Sin, that Chriſt was not an High-Prieſt on Earth, that he made no Satisfaction for Sin, that we are not juſtified by his Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, but our own, that the wicked ſhall be utterly anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilated at the laſt Day: Theſe he contended for in their Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods, and prevailed ſo by the Help of <hi>Smalcius</hi> and other Artifices, that in 24 Years he got his Opinions enthron'd in <hi>Poland,</hi> which are not rooted out to this Day.</p>
            <p>Whoſoever deſires to read more of this Hiſtory of Socinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm, may find much more in Dr. <hi>Owen's</hi> Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Biddle,</hi> and his Preface to it.</p>
            <p>Surely 'tis a thouſand Pitties that in <hi>England,</hi> a <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhen,</hi> a Land of Light, where the Goſpel-Sun hath ſhined in its Meridian Splendor, ſuch black Fogs ſhould riſe out of
<pb facs="tcp:56998:4"/> the bottomleſs Pit as to darken our Horizon: <hi>Trinitas,</hi> ſaith one, <hi>eſt verae Theologiae Fundamentum, quae conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequentes omnes fere Doctrinas quaſi animat:</hi> Who ſo denies the Trinity, denies his Baptiſm; for we are baptized in, or into the Name of Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt. It's true, the <hi>Racovian</hi> Catechiſm aſſerts Three, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounces them to be no Chriſtians who do not believe it; but deny that there are three Perſons or Subſiſtences in the God-head. But our Divines prove it by the Eſſential Name, <hi>Jehovah,</hi> eſſential Properties, Operations: But ſee more of this in the enſuing Treatiſe.</p>
            <p>The other dangerous and damnable Doctrine is that of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the Lord that bought us, <hi>2 Pet. 2. 1.</hi> revived out of the Rubbiſh of ancient Hereſies. Who could imagine that <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Turks</hi> ſhould be bred in <hi>England?</hi> Denying Chriſt's Divinity doth cut the very Sinews of our Hopes of Redemption and Conſolation: Neither Angels nor Men could have pacifyed God's Wrath, or ſatisfied Juſtice, or brought in everlaſting Righteouſneſs: Such Doctrines undermine and pluck up the Pillars of our Chriſtian Religion; and yet in theſe licentious Days ſuch Hereſies are publickly broach'd by more learned Scholars, and ſome confident <hi>Ignoramus's.</hi> I have read that Quakers ſay, we deny the Perſon of him whom you call Chriſt, and affirm that they that expect to be ſaved by that Chriſt without them, will be damned in that Faith. O horrid Sacrilege, unheard of Impiety!</p>
            <p>Methinks the Queſtion of our bleſſed Lord, that non-pluſt the Phariſees, <hi>Mat. 22 45.</hi> ſhould puzzle theſe Antichriſtian Spirits that deny Chriſt's Divinity. [If <hi>David</hi> then call
<pb facs="tcp:56998:4"/> him Lord, how is he his Son?] Is the Son greater than the Father? Surely the God-head of the Meſſiah advanceth him above King <hi>David.</hi> Its true, the Plumb-line of Reaſon is too ſhort to fathom this Myſtery; but where Reaſon cannot wade Faith muſt ſwim, having ſo good a Card and Guide as the Holy Ghoſt: The Trinity of Perſons, and Hypoſtatical Union of God-head and Man-hood in Chriſt, being ſo fully revealed in Scripture, let us hold them faſt, and contend for them as our Free-hold.</p>
            <p>This is the Attempt and Deſign of the enſuing Treatiſe, which was put into my Hands by a very reverend and dear Brother, whoſe Praiſe is in the Goſpel, who is better known to the World by the ſucceſsful Fruits of his indefatiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Labours, ſounding <hi>viva voce,</hi> than by legible Characters in Scripture, having ſpent much Time and Strength in his peculiar Province, with much Advantage to the Church of God: His Learning and Capacity elevates him above his Fellows, ſo that he needs no Epiſtle of Commendation from me or any other Perſon; his own Works praiſe him in the Gate, and in the Conſciences of many<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thouſand: nor doth any (pruritus ſcripturiendi) Itch of appearing in Print, prompt him to this Undertaking, but purely a Zeal for God, his Cauſe, Truth, and Glory, and the preventing of young Students being poiſoned with Soul-deſtructive Errours, that have edged his upright Soul, and moved his able Hand to this uncouth Undertaking: It's true, the Manner of hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling this Subject is ſomething abſtruſe and intricate; for the Subject is high and profound, and above the Reach of ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Capacities; but I hope it may give ſome Satisfaction to the
<pb facs="tcp:56998:5"/> learned and ingenuous Reader, and that this and all other Helps Polemical and Practical, may be of Uſe to the Church, is the Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>March 11. 1697.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Thy Soul-Friend, O. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56998:5"/>
            <head>REFLECTIONS ON A LETTER Writ by a Nameleſs Author TO THE <hi>Reverend Clergy of both Univerſities,</hi> And on his Bold Reflections on the Trinity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IN the beginning of the Introduction, p. 3. § 1, 2. the<note place="margin">On Ch. 1.</note> Author would make the World believe that his deſign in this Letter is to get the beſt Light and Information he can to promote his Eternal Happineſs; and to engage the Learned Perſons to whom he Writes, to comply with his deſires in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king opportunity to ſatisfy him, and a great number of Pious Men who are affected with the ſame doubts, occaſioned by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions amongſt the Clergy about the Doctrine of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Had the Author acted with like Modeſty in other parts of his Letter as he does here, there might have been ſome ground to hope, that he had truly deſired for to get his doubts ſatisfied; but when he dares be ſo bold as to Aſſert frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the Doctrine of the Trinity is no better than a bundle of flat Contradictions, Who can believe that he had any other deſign in Writing, than to vent his blaſphemous Invectives againſt the Ever-bleſſed God, Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt?</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:56998:6"/>
            <p>His Diſcourſe §. 3. is idle vain Diſcourſe; for where will he find any Perſons who pretend to believe they know not what, (<hi>i. e.</hi>) empty ſounds, or words that have no Ideas fixed to them? If he have met with any ſuch Aſſes, he ſhould tell us who they are, and not caſt falſe Reflections upon all thoſe Learned Writers who have writ upon, and by undeniable Proofs from Holy Scripture defended the Churches received Doctrine about the Trinity.</p>
            <p>His Diſcourſe p. 4. § 4, 5. is to the like purpoſe, and ſuch wherein he ſhews himſelf a falſe Calumniator; for whereas he would perſwade, that new and wrong Trinities are dayly encreaſing, Authors having ſuch different Ideas of them, that there are almoſt as many Trinities as Writers; and ſo would make it be believ'd, that they do but ridicule the Chriſtian Religion and render it moſt abſurd and irrational, in obliging People to put their truſt in Three they know not what, and to pay Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip to each of them, when the meer Light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture obligeth Man not to Adore for God any thing but what he believes to be an Omniſcient and an Omnipotent Being, able to Know and Relieve his Wants; and that to pay Worſhip to any thing elſe, is Idolatry.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>1</label> It's a groſs and abominable untruth, that there are almoſt as many Trinities as Writers about them; I could eaſily ſhew that Learned and Orthodox Divines generally do ſweetly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord in their Judgments about the Trinity; and what if ſome few be found who differ from theſe, muſt therefore the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Doctrine be rejected? Where will he find that Chriſtian Doctrine which hath not been depraved and corrupted by ſome or others?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>2</label> But Secondly, Where will he find ſuch Writers about the Trinity, who would oblige People to put their Truſt in Three they know not what; and to Adore any for God but an Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent Omniſcient Being? As I do believe he cannot find one Writer about the Trinity who doth this, therefore muſt it not be groſs Calumny to Charge all with this?</p>
            <p>What follows in p. 4. N. 6, 7. (<hi>viz.</hi>) That the <hi>Trinitarians only agree in the ſame words, that ſcarce three of theſe venture to explain themſelves being of the ſame Mind, and they that have
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56998:6"/> publiſhed what they ſuppoſed the Three are, have faln into groſs Contradictions, plain Polytheiſm, or Sabellianiſm, that they deſtroy one anothers Hypotheſes, but raiſe none;</hi> needs no other Anſwer than to tell the Author, all ſuch Aſſertions are meer Falſhoods, and ſuch as the greateſt part of his Book is ſtuffed with, as will hereafter be more fully evidenced.</p>
            <p>We proceed then to Chapter II. and the Author's Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings<note place="margin">On Ch. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> upon the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed. And here we muſt tell the Author, that if there be any Jangling amongſt late Writers about the meaning of the word (<hi>Perſon</hi>) it is to be lamented; yet is this no great Argument that they do not believe the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed, Which ſaith, <hi>We are compell'd by the Chriſtian Verity to acknowledge every Perſon to be by himſelf God;</hi> becauſe doubtleſs all the ſaid Writers whatever elſe they may differ in, yet do acknowledge the ſame Chriſtian Verity; yea, we do humbly conceive that there is not any Writer about the Holy Trinity worthy to be taken notice of, but he do's ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge a Divine Perſon to be an Uncreate, Eternal, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible, Almighty Being, yea God Bleſſed for ever: And that it would be Idolatry to Worſhip him if he were not ſuch; but the Author in asking, <hi>Is it not a Demonſtration, that thoſe that pay the higheſt Adoration to a Perſon, have no different Ideas of God and a Divine Perſon?</hi> ſpeaks not ſo right and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curately; becauſe altho theſe by Adoring a Divine Perſon do acknowledge him to be God, yet they do not ſay that he is God, as abſolutely conſidered, but as limited by a Relative Property, and ſo the Ideas may differ: Therefore his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſcourſe, that we cannot have an higher Idea of God than that he is ſuch a Perſon, and to frame any other, it muſt be one that is lower, and conſequently Blaſphemy againſt God; is but vain, and idle Diſcourſe; for neither the one nor the other of theſe Ideas is either higher or lower, but equal; the one being of God as abſolutely conſidered, the other of him as limited by a Perſonal Property; and this he muſt be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forced to confeſs, or deny that Scripture <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 6. who <hi>being in the form of God thought it no robbery to be equal with God;</hi> for Ideas of Equals muſt be Equal.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:56998:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> As to what he adds—<hi>If a Perſon be God there can be no real difference between them;</hi> for which he quotes <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 3. <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That Phraſe (<hi>Real difference</hi>) is Homonymous; for if by real difference be meant ſuch, as that which is <hi>Rei a Re,</hi> we grant there is no real difference, becauſe God and a Divine Perſon, or firſt and ſecond Perſon, are not different Things or Beings; but if by real difference he mean no more than a true modal diſtinction, in oppoſition to feign'd and imaginary, then we do aſſert ſuch a difference or diſtinction; and the Scriptures by him quoted are ſo far from oppoſing this, that they do clearly evince it, as we ſhall ſee afterwards.</p>
            <p>What is contain'd in § 9. is as idle and impertinent; for granting that if a Man be an Animal, all that is contain'd in the Idea of Animal, muſt be contain'd in that of Man; what is this to the purpoſe? But as if he would correct his own Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinency, he pretends afterwards to ſpeak properly, truly, naturally, <hi>(viz.) Man is a Rational Animal, and a Rational Animal is a Man; They are only different words to expreſs the ſame Being;</hi> ſo (ſaith he) <hi>a Divine Perſon and God are convertible Terms;</hi> how abſurd this Diſcourſe is will eaſily appear, if the Diſſimilitude of the things compared, be conſidered; Man is defin'd by Rational Animal; Man is the thing defined, Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Animal the Definition; therefore theſe muſt needs be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertible Terms: But it is not ſo here, for neither is God the Thing defined, and Divine Perſon the Definition, nor is Divine Perſon the Thing defined, and God the Definition; So that its clear they are not in like manner convertible as Man and Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Animal. Surely the Author for all his pretending to Reaſon, might have been more Logical: But he tells us that</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>Nothing is contain'd in the Idea of God, but what is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd in the Idea of a Divine Perſon; and ſo on the contrary: And therefore the Terms are convertible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Author is bold and forward in Aſſerting, but as ſlow in Proving what he do's aſſert: Where will he find one who aſſerts the Trinity but he will tell him, That the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God as abſolutely conſidered is communicable to three Perſons; but the Divine Eſſence as limited by a perſonal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56998:7"/> is Incommunicable; and is there then no difference in the Ideas of theſe? He may as well tell us that Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and Incommunicability are the ſame, which ſure is a downright contradiction. He might do well to give over ſuch bold Aſſertions, till he can make better proof of them; or free them from moſt groſs abſurdity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But the Author would perſwade, That <hi>Perſon</hi> being a Term which we give to all Intelligent Beings, either Man, Angel, or God, as we have no different Ideas of Man, and a humane Perſon, or of Angel, and Angelical Perſon, ſo we have the ſame Idea of God, and a Divine Perſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This will not at all follow, except he could make it out, that Perſonality does flow from the Divine Eſſence after the ſame manner as it doth from the Angelical or Humane Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, which he can never do; for it flows from Angelical or Humane Eſſence, as Finite and Terminated in it ſelf, but ſo it cannot flow from the Divine Eſſence, it being Infinite and Unterminated: Therefore tho Eſſence or Fundamental Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence in an Angel or Man, being Finite and Terminated in it ſelf, can propagate only one modal Subſiſtence or Perſonality, yet it will not follow by any Rational Conſequence, That the Divine Eſſence or Fundamental Subſiſtence which is Infinite and Unterminated, muſt do the like. Thus you ſee this high pretended Rationaliſt, how weak and vain his Reaſoning is. But you will ſee more of the Poyſon of this Doctrine in that which follows, (<hi>viz.) God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is in holy Writ deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed as a Perſon; and as the Father, who is a Perſon, is God, ſo God</hi> (as appears by a great number of Texis) <hi>is a Perſon,</hi> viz. <hi>the Father: So that it is evident there is nothing more in the Idea of one, than of the other, and are convertible Terms, and only diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent words which ſignifie the ſelf ſame All. perfect Being.</hi> Compare this paſſage with what we find p 32. in his cloſe of the <hi>9th</hi> Chapter, <hi>viz. That it is evident, that in Scripture God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is as much diſtinguiſhed from the Son, as two Men or Angels can be:</hi> So you ſee its clear, the Author's miſchievous deſign in denying the Bleſſed Trinity, is to overthrow and deſtroy (ſo far as in him lies) The Divinity of Chriſt and of the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Spirit: for in making the Perſon of the Father and God
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56998:8"/> convertible Terms, he excludes the Son and bleſſed Spirit from being God, yea he makes God and the Son to differ as really, as two Men or Angels. So that you ſee his Work is to revive again the long ſince confu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed and condemned Hereſies and Blaſphemies wherewith <hi>Arius</hi> did ſo much infeſt the ancient Church, raiſing a dreadful Storm in it. One would think that thoſe many Scripture Texts, which, with greateſt Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, do hold forth the Divinity of Chriſt and of the Holy Ghoſt, ſuch as <hi>Iſa. 9. 6. Joh 1. 1, 2, 3, 10. Joh. 17. 5. Heb. 1. 8, 9, 10, 11, 12. Pſal. 139. 7. Act. 5. 3, 4. I Cor.</hi> 2. 10, 11. with abundance more, ſhould have kept him from ſo daring an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt as to vent himſelf in downright Oppoſition to ſo many ſacred Teſtimonies.</p>
            <p>As to what follows, p. 6. §. 10. he tells us (1.) That <hi>he hath, according to his weak Ability, uindicated the Honour of a Divine Perſon, and clear'd the</hi> Athanaſian <hi>Creed from ſpeaking ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptibly of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Author's running into groſs Miſtakes about <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Divine Perſon,</hi> argues indeed but weak Ability; but it were well if Weakneſs were the worſt; ſurely his excluding the Son, as well as Spirit, from being God or Divine Perſon, is ſo far from vindicating the Honour of Divine Perſon, that it caſts the vileſt Aſperſions, not only on the ever-bleſſed God, but alſo on holy Scripture, which teſtifies, that Father, Word, and Holy Ghoſt, are one, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 7. But when he tells us, he hath cleared the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed from ſpeaking ſo contemptibly of him, (<hi>viz. Divine Perſon</hi>) It's ſtrange if he can believe himſelf, when a little after he tells us, that <hi>this good charitable Creed only damns all thoſe that cannot believe a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſon is and is not the ſame with God: And that it makes it Damnation not to believe a Difference.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is it not evident here, that his Deſign, in Reference to this Creed, is only to ridicule it, and ſo ſet it off, as made up of Contradictions (when yet the Contradictions are not found in the Creed, but only floating in his own Brain) yea, and to make the Compiler of it (the worthy <hi>Athanaſius</hi>) fall under the Fate of Damnation, if he believe his own Creed, as <hi>Sect.</hi> 1? And what is this but to damn all the Chriſtian
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56998:8"/> World from the Time that the <hi>Arian</hi> Hereſy was exploded in it, till ſuch time as it was reviv'd again by <hi>Socinus;</hi> yea, and to rob God of a Church during thoſe many hundred Years?</p>
            <p>But how comes this great Maſter of Reaſon to be ſo highly conceited of himſelf, as to account all the ancient Fathers, in and ſince the Time of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> all the learned School-men and reformed Divines, to be a Pack of ſuch ſilly Fools, as to contradict themſelves, to ſay a thing and unſay it again, which is ſaying nothing at all, and to teach the People like Parrots, Propoſitions without apprehending them, and ſuch as are wholly unintelligible, and the laſt of which is a Negation of the firſt? See N. 11. How comes, I ſay, this Man to have this Confidence, or rather, bold Impudence? Is it from the Strength of his Reaſon, or rather, of his Folly? I would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly reduce his Reaſonings (if they will bear it) to ſome Heads, and then ſeverally conſider the Strength of each of them, for they are but a few, the far greateſt Part of his Book being made up of meer Tautologies.</p>
            <p>His firſt Reaſoning <hi>P.</hi> 6. §. 10. is grounded on his own grand Miſtake, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>God</hi> (abſolutely conſidered) and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> are convertible Terms, ſo that there muſt be as many Gods as Perſons. How falſe this is, hath been before declared and evidenced, ſo that I ſhall not trouble my Reader with it again.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> His ſecond Reaſoning immediately follows in the ſame Page, and it ſeems to be to this purpoſe; <hi>If there are Three, each of whom is God, or each of whom is Infinite, Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Incomprehenſible, then there are three Gods, three Almighties, three Infinites,</hi> &amp;c. His Conſequence is moſt abſurd and falſe, becauſe all the three Perſons have but one and the ſame ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar or numerical God-head, Infinity, Omnipotency, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for neither is the divine Eſſence, or any Eſſential Attribute of God multiply'd as Perſonality is. But the Author asks, <hi>How do you prove that there are three Almighties, three Incomprehenſible Perſons?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We affirm no ſuch thing, let ſuch prove it as do aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it; for tho <hi>three</hi> may be affirmed of <hi>Perſons,</hi> becauſe mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicable,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56998:9"/> yet not of <hi>infinite</hi> or <hi>eternal,</hi> which cannot be multiplied; ſo that his Argument is a meer Sophiſm (<hi>viz.</hi>) ſuch as ariſeth <hi>e Conjunctione eorum quae dividenda ſunt,</hi> and may be anſwered thus, God is three Perſons, but not three In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finites or Eternals; neither will he ever be able, if he had more Skill than he hath, from a Trinity of Perſons in God, if rightly underſtood, to infer Polytheiſm, or a Plurality of Gods.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> His third way of Reaſoning (if we may call it ſuch) is <hi>P.</hi> 7. §. 13. The former Part of the Section is a meer Repetition of what went before, and hath been fully anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But in the latter Part of it, he tells us, <hi>That God and Man</hi> (he means according to the Trinitarian Doctrine) <hi>are <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals, and ſo predicated of more Perſons than one, and each Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſon is as much of himſelf God</hi> (he means a diſtinct God) <hi>as each Human Perſon is Man</hi> (i. e. <hi>diſtinct Man.</hi>)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Never any Trinitarian yet did aſſume God to be an Univerſal, or to be predicated of Father, Son, and Spirit, <hi>per Modum Generis ſeu <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſalis.</hi> We ſay, as in the Creed, The Father is God, the Son is God, and the Holy Ghoſt is God; that is, the Father is Eternal God, as with the Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Property of Father, the Son is the ſame Eternal God, but with a diſtinct Perſonal Property (<hi>viz.</hi>) that of Son, the like we ſay of the Holy Spirit: Therefore his Inference, <hi>That Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſons muſt be as much diſtinct as Humane Perſons,</hi> is idle and vain; and it ſtands firm (for all he hath ſaid) that there are not three Gods, but one God.</p>
            <p>As to what he adds, §. 15. <hi>That Father, and Son, being Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, cannot ſubſist in the ſame Subject,</hi> I muſt tell him, that, had he learned his Logick better, he would have found they may, provided they be not predicated <hi>de eodem reſpectu ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem,</hi> which theſe are not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> His fourth way of arguing is, §. 16. <hi>If the Son is the ſame God, as he is that begat a Son, he muſt beget a Son too, except the ſame God did and did not beget a Son.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Although the Son be the ſame as he is that begot, yet he does not beget, becauſe God, as begetting, is God, as cloathed with the Relative Property of Father; now the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56998:9"/> Son not being cloathed with that Property, doth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get.</p>
            <p>His fifth way of Reaſoning, §. 18. is as fooliſh and abſurd <hi>viz. That if God be three Perſons, and each Perſon God, there muſt be nine Perſons, becauſe each ſingle Perſon muſt be three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</hi> Had the Author but known and weighed the Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion given of a Divine Perſon, <hi>viz. that he is—eſſentia Dei prout eſt cum Proprietate Hypoſtatica,</hi> he would not have trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled us with ſuch a trifling Argument. For altho God abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely conſidered, and not limited by a Perſonal Property, may, by Addition of thoſe Properties, be Three Perſons; yet a Divine Perſon, being God limited by Perſonal Property, cannot be Three Perſons.</p>
            <p>His ſixth way of arguing is §. 20. <hi>Thoſe things, according to the common Senſe of Mankind, are the ſame with themſelves that are the ſame with a third, and all Knowledge but Intuitive, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon the Truth of it.</hi> We grant him all this: But what is it he would infer? It's this, that if three Perſons and one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, firſt, ſecond, and third, are the ſame with God, they are the ſame with one another: Is this his Demonſtration? I muſt tell him, that through Abuſe of a good Rule, there's no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Confuſion and Deceit in it. For 1. He confounds three Perſons and one, as if they were the very ſame. 2. He would make us believe, that they do both alike agree in a third, which is abſurd and falſe, becauſe that Notion we have of the three Perſons jointly conſidered, is adequate to the Notion we have of God, becauſe the Divine Eſſence is not communicable to more than three Perſons: But the Notion we have of a ſingle Perſon is not adequate to the Notion we have of God, who is communicable to more than a ſingle Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Do theſe then agree entirely in a third, when this third hath it ſelf, after a different manner, with reſpect to them? It cannot be: So that the Argument may be retorted upon himſelf, and the quite contrary Concluſion inferred from the foreſaid Rule. Thus, if one Perſon and three Perſons do not agree in a third, then they do not agree between themſelves, but they do not agree in a third (as hath been ſhewn) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not between themſelves.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:56998:10"/>
            <p>His ſeventh way of arguing, § 21. is to as little purpoſe; <hi>If the Perſons</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>are really diſtinct, and each is God, must not each be God diſtinct from the other? For nothing can be diſtinctly predicated of three diſtinct Perſons, if it do not diſtinctly belong to each.</hi> As to the phraſe of <hi>real Diſtinction,</hi> we refer the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to what hath been ſaid upon §. 8. But as to what follows, we ſay, That altho God be predicated of three diſtinct Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, yet not diſtinctly, or after a diſtinct manner, but one and the ſame God is after one and the ſame manner equally predicated of three, therefore it follows (quite contrary to what he would infer) that there's but one ever bleſſed God, tho three diſtinct Perſons. His <hi>22d.</hi> Section hath been an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered over and over.</p>
            <p>All that which he adds, §. 23, 24, 27, 28. is wholly founded upon his own groſs Miſtakes, as if it muſt needs follow from a Multiplication of Perſons that there muſt be a Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of Infinities and All-ſufficiencies in God; for ſuppoſe he may find ſome Aſſertors of the Trinity to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſuch a manner of ſpeaking, as to call the three Perſons, <hi>three Infinite Perſons,</hi> or <hi>three All-ſufficient Perſons,</hi> yet he knows well enough, in his own Conſcience, that they mean no more than three Perſons, with one and the ſame Numeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Infinity and All-ſufficiency; or which is the ſame, <hi>tres perſonas habentes eandem ſingularem infinitatem &amp; omni-ſufficienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am:</hi> And that they do account it the vileſt Hereſy, yea, even Blaſphemy, to aſſert a Plurality of Infinities and All-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencies in God; and does it not argue then the Author to be guilty of the vileſt Sophiſm and Deceit; yea, ſuch as is more ſuitable for the Devil, the Father of Lyes, than for any fair Diſputant, from an Homonymous Phraſe that may be taken in different, yea, contrary Senſes, to infer, from ſuch a Senſe or Interpretation as he puts on the Phraſe, Heretical and Blaſphemous Concluſions, as the Concluſions of ſuch Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, as he knows do take and interpret the ſame Phraſe in a quite contrary Senſe? Let him but take the Phraſe in the Senſe of theſe Authors, and all his monſtrous Concluſions will va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh. He can neither infer, that there are three Infinites, or Infinities, or three Infinite Spaces, or three Gods, or that the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56998:10"/> Trinitarians muſt be Idolaters, either in worſhipping ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing as God which is not God, or in ſetting up a Plurality of Gods, as he would perſwade §. 30. Theſe will be found to be Brats of his own luxuriant Brain, not to be laid at the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians Door. As to what he adds, §. 31. <hi>That whatever Name we give the three, yea, tho we only ſay three, yet ſo long as we pay Divine Worſhip to each, we own three Gods, becauſe the three are three Objects of Divine Worſhip, and whilſt the one is worſhipped, the other is not worſhipped,</hi> &amp;c. We ſhall anſwer this hereafter, <hi>viz. P.</hi> 24. when we come to confute this falſe and frivolous Charge more largely elſewhere inſiſted on by the Author: Becauſe we do not love, with him, to multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply Tautologies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> There's only one thing more I would take into Conſideration before I leave this Chapter, that I may leave this Author the more inexcuſable in his perverſe Reaſoning ſuch as he makes uſe of, Section 25, 26. His Words are theſe (<hi>viz.) There cannot be ſuppoſed in God more Perſons than one, without ſuppoſing an infinite Number; for what Reaſon ſoever moved the firſt Perſon to beget two Perſons equal to himſelf, the ſame Reaſon (becauſe their Nature is the ſame) muſt move the other to beget their Equals, and ſo on to Infinity; for</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>if the firſt Perſon produced two equal to himſelf, it was no doubt an eſſential Perfection of his Nature, otherwiſe he might have choſen whether he would have produced them, and they, when produced, would have had but a precarious dependent Being, ſince they muſt depend on his Pleaſure for their Continuance in Being, as well as for their Being.</hi> And he does further infer, <hi>that if no more Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons can now be produced, then an Eſſential Property is loſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The whole of his Diſcourſe do's clearly evince, that the Author had blind and groſs Conceptions about the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Generation of the Son, and Miſſion or Emiſſion of the Bleſſed Spirit, and therefore it's no wonder to find his whole Diſcourſe made up of thoſe two grand Ingredients, Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Ignorance. For,</p>
            <p>1. How ſhamefully does he contradict himſelf, when he tells us, that if the firſt Perſon produced two equal to himſelf. it was no doubt an Eſſential Perfection of his Nature, and yet
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56998:11"/> (as §. 25.) that it was for ſome Reaſon that moved him to it: How can both theſe hold? If the Act was an Eſſential Perfection, then it was no arbitrary Act; but if it was an Act, to which the Agent was moved by ſome Reaſon, then it was arbitrary and not eſſential: If his Adverſaries ſpoke Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions at ſuch a rate as this, he might then have had Ground to have charged theſe on them.</p>
            <p>2. What a begetting Act muſt that be, which may, or rather muſt (according to him) be multiplyed into infinite begetting Acts? But had he framed no other Ideas of Eternal Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Eternal Miſſion, but ſuch as might have ſuited with the Nature of the moſt perfect eternal Spirit, he would then have ſeen, that that moſt ſublime and ſcriptural Revelation of three Perſons in the God-head, is not only ſweetly conſiſtent with the higheſt Reaſon, but likewiſe, that it's impoſſible that there ſhould be more than three Perſons in the God-head.</p>
            <p>Had the Author but peruſed, and ſeriouſly weighed what is ſaid as to this, by the learned and accurate Doctor <hi>Ames,</hi> in his <hi>Medulla Theologiae, ch.</hi> 5 §. 16. (and which is agreeable to what hath been ſaid before by ancient Fathers, School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and modern Divines) ſure he would not have talked at ſuch a rate as he doth; the Doctor here ſpeaking of a Trinity of Perſons in God. hath theſe Words, <hi>viz. poteſt tamen (ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua ex parte) ſimilitudine adumbrari; Pater nempe est quaſi Deus intelligens; Filius Imago Patris expreſſa, eſt quaſi Deus intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectus; Spiritus ſanctus emanans, a Patre per Filium &amp; ſpiratus eſt quaſi Deus dilectus; Filius producitur quaſi per actum intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendi ex intellectu vel memoriâ faecundâ Patris; Spiritus ſanctus producitur per actum amandi vel ſpirandi ex voluntate faecunda Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris &amp; Filii.</hi> What I pray will the Author ſay to ſuch a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe as this? (1.) Will he ſay that God doth not know himſelf by a reflex Act of eternal Intellection terminated on himſelf? Surely this he neither can nor dare do. 2. Will he ſay, that God doth not, after a like manner, terminate an eternal Act of Dilection on himſelf? He cannot ſay this. (3.) Can he aſſure us that Perſonalities in God cannot flow from ſuch reflex Acts? I am ſure he cannot. (4.) Are there any moreinternal and eternal reflex Acts in God, beſides the two
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56998:11"/> before mentioned, from which Perſonalities can flow, and can there any more than three Perſonalities flow from theſe in manner aforeſaid, ſuppoſing theſe to emane from the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Eſſence, by Mediation of the ſaid Acts? I ſhall freely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs here, we could not at all have gone thus far by the dim Light of our own Reaſon, nor could ſo much as have thought no, much leſs, have aſſerted a Trinity of Perſons in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Divine Eſſence; but when we have the great and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſſed God going before us in the infallible Revelation of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scripture, and aſſuring us, that there be Three that bear Witneſs in Heaven, and that theſe Three are One; that him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as Father, did, before the World was, and from Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, beget the Son, in the Form of God, and equal to himſelf; that the Holy Ghoſt, in like manner, is God, proceeding and ſent from the Father and Son; we can now ſafely follow God, and improve ſanctified Reaſon to the getting of true and right Notions about this ſublime Myſtery, and for Defence and Vindication of it, and diſpelling the Miſts of thoſe vile Aſperſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and ſeigned Contradictions, black-mouth'd Hereticks would faſten on it; and we can as truly tell the Author, that however this Myſtery be a very high Myſtery, yet it is not (as he would perſwade) wholly unintelligible, but that we may have true Ideas of the Father begetting, and of the Son's being begotten, and of the Holy Ghoſt's proceeding from Eternity; and that this was not after ſome groſs manner as the Author ſeems to ſuppoſe, but in ſuch a way, as might agree to the moſt pure and ſimple Spirit; yea, we may tell him, that from one and the ſame numerical eternal Eſſence acting upon its ſelf by its internal Acts, and likewiſe terminating thoſe Acts, and ſo laying the Foundations of relative Properties, Three rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive perſonal Properties, with the Three bleſſed eternal Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, do neceſſarily emane, without the leaſt Appearance of a Contradiction; the divine Eſſence ſo acting or reflecting on its ſelf by eternal Intellection with the relative Property of Generation, as flowing from it, being God the Father: The divine Eſſence as reflected on by, and terminating the ſaid In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellection with its relative Property (of being begotten) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God the Son, the Splendor of the Father's Glory, the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56998:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:56998:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:56998:13"/> eternal <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or the expreſs Image of the Father's Perſon, making a full and entire Repreſentation thereof: (And how agreeable is this to many Scripture Phraſes, relating to the the Perſon of the Son?) And the ſame divine Eſſence, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected on or terminated by that other Act of the ſame Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and which may be ſtil'd the Love or Dilection of the Father and Son, with its relative Property of being ſent or proceding, being the third Perſon, or Holy Ghoſt, the amiable Spring-head and Fountain of all that good which God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municates to his Creatures, the all-ſearching, quickning Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, <hi>Deus ſpiratus miſſus,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>And give me leave to ask the Author, our high pretended Rationaliſt (who dares, with his dark and glimmering Light, ſo boldly contradict divine Revelation; telling us, that for the Father to beget, the Son to be begotten, the Holy Ghoſt to proceed; and that theſe Three ſhould be One, and the Son to be equal to God the Father; that ſuch Language is nothing but mere Contradictions, tho the expreſs Language of the written Word.) Let me ask him, I ſay; according to the preceding Interpretation of the Words, what Shew or leaſt Appearance of a Contradiction can he find in them? For the Divine Eſſence, by an eternal reflex Act to know its ſelf; and ſo, by a like act, to love it ſelf, and for the ſame Eſſence to terminate each act, is that which he neither can nor dare de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; becauſe that theſe are eſſential divine Perfections falling under our diſtinct inadequate Notions of the ſame glorious Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and which can no more ceaſe to be, than God can ceaſe to be God; where then comes in his Contradiction?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Will he ſay, that according to theſe our Notions of a Trinity, it follows that there are but three Perſons, and yet nine Perſons? That they cannot be multiplyed beyond three, and yet may be multiplyed <hi>in infinitum?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The quite contrary follows: For, according to theſe our Notions of the divine Eſſence ſo acting upon it ſelf, as aforeſaid, and ſo terminating the ſaid two internal eſſential acts, (<hi>viz.</hi>) of Intellect and Will; it's impoſſible the Perſons in the divine Eſſence, as flowing from them, ſhould either fall ſhort or exceed the Number Three; becauſe, according to theſe.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56998:13"/> theſe, we have (to come up to his own Terms) diſtinct Ideas of ſo many, and neither fewer nor more, (<hi>viz.</hi>) of a Perſon acting or begetting, of a Perſon conceived or begotten, and of a Perſon beloved or proceeding. But will he ſay (as he doth expreſly) §. 26. That,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj. If it be not eſſential to the Nature of the Son and Spirit, ſo to produce more Perſons equal to themſelves, their Nature is not the ſame with the Father's, and they want Perfections which he hath?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It's eſſential to the Nature of Son and Spirit, as well as of the Father, abſolutely conſidered to be productive of more equal Perſons, tho it be not eſſential to the Nature of the Son and Spirit as limited by perſonal Property; becauſe, by theſe, it's rendred incommunicable, and cannot be ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductive. Therefore it's very idle what he would infer, that the Nature of the Son and Spirit, is not the ſame with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's, becauſe they want Perfections which he has, becauſe the Nature ſtill, whether of Father, Son, or Spirit, abſolutely conſidered as ſuch, hath the very ſame eſſential Perfections, tho, as this is limited by perſonal Properties, importing three Perſons actually to exiſt in it from Eternity, it cannot be ſaid to produce them <hi>de novo,</hi> and to be ſtill productive of them; ſo that we may juſtly ſay here, that whoſoever ſhall affirm, that Eſſence, as common to Father, Son, and Spirit, is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductive of Three Perſons, let him be <hi>Anathema;</hi> and whoever ſhall affirm, that Eſſence, as limited to Father, Son and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, by perſonal Properties, is ſtill productive of Three Perſons <hi>de novo,</hi> let him be <hi>Anathema;</hi> for Eſſence ſo limited, the Three Perſons exiſt as actually produced, and therefore cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main to be produced.</p>
            <p>Again, will the Author ſay, that the Father now producing no Perſons equal to himſelf, has loſt a Perfection that's eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to his Nature, and conſequently ceaſeth to be all perfect, as §. 26? How vain and idle is all this? When the act of beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or producing in God, is eſſential to the divine Nature, and ſo can no more ceaſe to be, than the Nature it ſelf, it being an eternal act identified with the Nature, and an eternal Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch Relation as that of Son to Father, which muſt there.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56998:14"/> therefore be continued for ever, the Foundation being continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed otherwiſe than in the Creatures.</p>
            <p>Having premiſed thus much for Explication of a Myſtery, which the Author moſt blaſphemouſly pretends to be a Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Anti-Chriſt, wholly inexplicabable and unintelligible; and having ſhewed that however it be a moſt ſublime Myſtery, much tranſcending Reaſon and the Light of Nature, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once fully reveal'd in the Word, that it's ſo far from ſtanding in flat Contradiction, to Reaſon and natural Light, that it's found to have a ſweet Conſiſtency with Reaſon and Light of Nature.</p>
            <p>Having, I ſay, permiſed thus much, I proceed now to his<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 3.</note> third Chapter of the <hi>Nominal Trinitarians,</hi> as the Author thinks meet (tho without juſt Ground) to ſtile theſe Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the Trinity, whom he doth diſtinguiſh from ſuch as he doth after call <hi>Real Trinitarians</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here, before I paſs on, give me leave to obſerve, that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever moſt orthodox Divines tell us (ſee <hi>Polan. Syntag. p.</hi> 226.) That the Diſtinction of the divine Perſons ought to be the leaſt Diſtinction: Therefore Counſels and Fathers generally ſay, that it's Relation only that makes Diſtinction and Number in God; yet, however, they all agree in Oppoſition to <hi>Sabelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> that this is not meer nominal, but a true Diſtinction; which will hereafter be further evidenced.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> And, now to come to the Chapter it ſelf; where, firſt, I ſhall take notice of that Paſſage of the Author, §. 35. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that being anſwered, the Solution of his other Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons will be very Facile, or rather, the Objections will vaniſh of themſelves: His Words are theſe; <hi>It contradicts our cleareſt Ideas, to ſuppoſe the ſame numerical Subſtance that is in one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to be at the ſame time in another; and we can as little appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend what we mean when we ſay the ſame numerical Subſtance con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes three infinite Perſons, as when we ſay, the ſame Subſtance conſtitutes three finite Perſons. Is not the reaſon the ſame between an infinite Perſon and an infinite Subſtance, and between a finite Perſon and a finite Subſtance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> As to that Homonymous Phraſe (<hi>three infinite Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi>) I have ſhewn before in what Senſe it may be allowed, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56998:14"/> and in what Senſe it may not, and therefore ſhall not here trouble my ſelf or the Reader with it again; but as to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of his Diſcourſe, I muſt tell him, that altho it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicts our cleareſt Ideas, to ſuppoſe the ſame numerical finite Subſtance that is in one finite Perſon, to be at the ſame time in another; yet it no way contradicts our cleareſt Ideas, that the ſame numerical infinite Subſtance that is in one Perſon, with one Mode of Subſiſtence, ſhould be at the ſame time in another Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, with a different Mode of Subſiſtence. Neither is the reaſon the ſame between an infinite Perſon and infinite Subſtance, and between a finite Perſon and a finite Subſtance. And his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake about this is the Foundation of all his other Miſtakes, and Soul-ruining Errors. That the Reaſon is not the ſame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween infinite Subſtance and infinite Perſon, as it is between fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Subſtance and finite Perſon, is evident; becauſe finite Subſtance does propagate modal Subſiſtence (which in ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Nature we call Perſonality) as it's finite and terminated; yea, and where it hath its Terms; but infinite Subſtance, not being ſo terminated, but infinitely excluding all Terms and Bounds, cannot therefore propagate Perſonality in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as the finite doth; for that would be to make it imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; and if it doth not propagate this after the ſame manner, then it follows undeniably, that the Reaſon is not the ſame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt infinite Subſtance and infinite Perſon or Perſonality, as between finite Subſtance and finite Perſon or Perſonality: So that this Author's ſelf-evident Propoſitions will be found to be ſelf-evident Untruths; and his Reaſoning is no better when he would infer, that becauſe the ſame numerical finite Subſtance is but in one Perſon, therefore infinite muſt be ſo too.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But he would perſwade, that if, by reaſon of the Difference between finite and infinite, there is a Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Number of Perſons, that the Subſtance is in; it would follow, that the Difference of Number is infinite, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the infinite Diſtance betwixt theſe would ſuppoſe this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Reaſoning of his is vain and falſe as the former, for as Scripture is expreſs in it, that there's Three, and no greater Number of Perſons in God, than three, <hi>viz.</hi> Father, Son, and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; ſo we have ſhewn how ſanctified Reaſon ſweetly complies with
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56998:15"/> with divine Revelation in giving us clear Ideas of it, how Three and no more than Three perſonal Properties may emane or flow from divine Eſſence, as terminating it ſelf by eſſential internal Acts upon it ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But ſuppoſe the Author ſhould here object, if three re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative Properties or Perſonalities flow from divine Eſſence by means of reflex acts of Eſſence; how comes it to paſs that theſe do not in like manner flow from angelical or humane Eſſence, reflecting on it ſelf after a like manner by the like Acts?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There's not the like Reaſon for it. 1. Becauſe theſe internal reflex Acts of Intellection and Dilection in the angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and humane Nature, are but accidental acts, and moſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently intermitted, and therefore cannot propagate Perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities; but in the Divine Nature theſe are eſſential eternal acts, and therefore may (I had almoſt ſaid muſt) propagate ſomething (<hi>viz.</hi>) in that Nature whence they emane, and whereon they terminate. 2. Theſe reflex acts in the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, at leaſt in our ſelves, are very imperfect, and cannot produce an expreſs Image of that which reflects, on the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as reflected on, and conſequently not a Perſon: But in God theſe are moſt perfect, and therefore produce that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Image which is a Perſon, and ſo the Son is ſtiled, <hi>Heb. 1. 3. The expreſs Image of the Father's Perſon.</hi> 3. We have ſhew'd before, that angelical or humane Eſſence being finite, and having Terms, muſt therefore, where-ever it terminates, or where the utmoſt Bounds of its Extenſion are, propagate Modal Subſiſtence or Perſonality for to terminate ſuch Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; but the divine Eſſence, infinitely exceeding all ſuch Bounds and Limits, cannot in this way (ſuited only to a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Creature) propagate the ſame; but doth it after an high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er way, ſuited to infinite immenſe Being. And here I would demand of the Author, either to ſhew us the way wherein in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite eſſence doth this, ſeeing it's undenyable that it muſt be different from this of finite Beings; or elſe give us ſome preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Reaſons, why it may not do it by terminating it ſelf up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it ſelf, with the aforeſaid reflex acts, or elſe ingenuouſly confeſs, that a Trinity of Perſons, or which is the ſame, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, and Spirit in one and the ſame ſingular divine Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56998:15"/> is not only clearly reveal'd in the written Word, but is likewiſe very fully conſiſtent with true Reaſon and the Light of Nature, as elevated and improved by divine Revelation; and that he hath greateſt Cauſe to be humbled, for his bold blaſphemous Oppoſitions to ſo great and clear a Truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> And thus, having diſcovered the Falſehood of his grand Concluſion, §. 35. I proceed to take notice of ſome few things more in this Chapter, eſpecially in §. 33. where we find him thus reaſoning.—<hi>If a Perſon be a Subſtance, there must be three Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, becauſe Subſtance is contained in the Idea of Perſon, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, as many Subſtances as Perſons;</hi> all that we apprehend of a divine Subſtance is, that he is a Subject, in which all the divine At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes exiſt; that Perſon is the very ſame, and theſe are only dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Words to expreſs the divine Being by, whence he would infer (moſt blaſphemouſly) §. 34. <hi>That a Trinity of Perſons in one Subſtance, is nothing leſs than a Trinity of Contradictions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But I muſt tell the Author, that the whole of this his Diſcourſe and Reaſoning, is full of Confuſion, Deceit, and Error, and might, at leaſt, in Part, have been rectified by himſelf, had he been well vers'd in ſound Philoſophy, and if he had but aſſented to ſome common Maxims granted by learned Men; for, 1. He confounds Subſtance and ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Nature or Eſſence, as when he makes it to be the proper Subject of eſſential Attributes: So <hi>p.</hi> 28. of his Book, §. 85. he tells us, <hi>If the Father communicated his Eſſence to the Son, he communicated himſelf, who is no way diſtinct from the Eſſence;</hi> but Philoſophers tell him (ſee <hi>Gliſſon de Nat. Subſt. p.</hi> 6.) that Subſtance is made up of two Principles, which they call <hi>Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta Subſtantialia (viz.</hi>) ſubſtantial Eſſence, and modal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence, which, in Rational Nature, is call'd Perſonality, and ſo would have taught, that he ought not to confound theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> the Part with the Whole, or <hi>Principium cum Principiato,</hi> which none but a Novice in Philoſophy would have done. 2. Having (as before) confounded or identified compleat Subſtance or ſubſtantial Eſſence, he confounds again this his Subſtance and ſubſtantial Eſſence, with Perſon or Perſonality, contrary to the Rules of all Philoſophy, yea, even of ſuch as relate to created Subſtances (about which he takes his Ideas to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56998:16"/> be moſt clear, and boaſts of them as common Ideas of all Mankind,) for might he not have found Philoſophers not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd about the Trinity, from meer Dictates of Reaſon and natural Light, telling him (<hi>viz.</hi>) that <hi>eſſentia ſubſtantialis eſt ſingularis ſubſtantia continens integram individui entitatem.</hi> Or, <hi>abſtracto ſumptam, ſeu totum id quod abſtrahiturè ſuppoſito:</hi> And that Modal Subſiſtence, Suppoſitality,, or (which in Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Nature is the ſame) Perſonality, is <hi>Modus ab eſſentia ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiali reſultans, eam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> quod ammodo terminans;</hi> and that it is, <hi>To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um id post abſtractionem minutilum in ſuppoſito reſiduum, quod eſſentiae additum eam concertioni reſtituit.</hi> All which is ſo clear, that if he dare yet venture to deny any Part of it, I hope he may, by one familiar Inſtance, be forc't to confeſs the Truth, and correct his Error, or elſe expoſe himſelf to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Scorn of Manking: We ſay that <hi>Homo habet Humanita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem,</hi> or which is the ſame, <hi>eſſentiam humanam ſubſtantialem:</hi> It is the common Language of Men, that Man is that Perſon, who hath ſubſtantial humane Eſſence: But ſhould the Author ſay, that <hi>Homo habet hominem, that Man hath Man,</hi> or that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Perſon, which is himſelf, would he not render himſelf too apertly ridiculous to all Manking? And doth not this undeny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably evince, that there is more in the Perſon of a Man as being the <hi>totum cotinens,</hi> than there is in ſubſtantial humane Eſſence, which is but <hi>pars contenta;</hi> for ſubſtantial humane Eſſence can be nothing but Eſſence; but Man beſides that Eſſence hath Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonality, and is made up of both, as conſtituent Principles; and this is ſtill further evinced, both by the the vulgar Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that is given of a Perſon, <hi>viz.</hi> that he is, <hi>ſubſtantia intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectualis naturae ſingularis incommunicabilis,</hi> and alſo by that which Writers in Theology generally give of a divine Perſon, <hi>viz.</hi> that he is, <hi>eſſentia Dei prout eſt cum proprietate hypoſtatica,</hi> or to that purpoſe; and theſe I was more willing to lay down here, not only for fuller Explication of the matter in hand, but alſo becauſe the Author ſeems to call for them, in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of his Letter, §. 36. telling us, that according to theſe Ideas we have of Subſtance, or (as he means) ſubſtantial Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and Perſon, it is a flat Contradiction to ſay there are three of the one, and but one of the other; and that if we
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56998:16"/> have no Ideas, we talk like Parrots, when we affirm or deny any thing concerning any thing we have no Ideas of: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, 1. I would, by theſe Definitions, let the Author ſee (tho he cannot here pretend Ignorance, becauſe they are the vulgar Definitions) that we have Ideas of Subſtance and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; yea, clear Ideas, tho not ſuch as his.</p>
            <p>2. Whereas he ſaith, according to thoſe Ideas we have of Subſtance and Perſon; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſhould have ſaid from thoſe groſs Ideas<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which my ſelf and the Anti-trinitarian Faction have of Subſtance and Perſon, ſuch a Concluſion as that before (ſo blaſphemous that I tremble to write it) may be inferred; no wonder, when theſe ſay that the Idea of ſubſtantial Eſſence, Subſtance and Perſon, is entirely one and the ſame, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found one of theſe with another, contrary to common Senſe and Reaſon, as we have ſhewn; but for him to ſay, that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thoſe Ideas which we have of Subſtance, Perſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If he mean the vulgar Ideas of the beſt and moſt acurate Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines and Philoſophers, as he ſeems to do; then I muſt tell him, 1. That it is but one of his cunning falſe Tricks, by ranking himſelf in the Number of theſe, to inſinuate into his incautious Reader, that his Idea of Subſtance and Perſon are the ſame with the vulgar Ideas of the beſt Divines and Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers; when it's evident, from the aforeſaid Definitions, they are not the ſame; for his Idea of Perſon is no way di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from that of ſubſtantial Eſſence, as he doth expreſly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, when he tells us, <hi>p. 23. §. 85. That God the Father is no ways diſtinct from his Eſſence;</hi> but now the Idea of Philoſophers as well as Divines, according to the ſaid vulgar Definitions, is diſtinct, becauſe their Idea of ſubſtantial Eſſence, being but one (tho the chief) Rudiment of a Perſon, doth exclude the Idea of Modal Subſiſtence or Perſonality; the other Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as hath been ſhewn, when yet the Idea of Perſon (as is granted) does include both. And I pray then, how are theſe the ſame? 2. Having thus declard what our true Ideas are of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l Eſſence, Subſtance, Perſon, and differenc'd them from his falſe Ideas; I would now know of him, what flat Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction there is in our affirming Three Perſons, and yet but one ſubſtantial Eſſence or Subſtance in God; and we ſhall ſee how
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56998:17"/> he makes this out, §. 37. He reaſons thus. <hi>If the Perſons are the ſame Subſtance, or</hi> (which is the ſame in his Senſe) <hi>ſubſtantial Eſſence, then the ſame Subſtance or ſubſtantial Eſſence, is begotten and unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, and yet neither of theſe, but proceeding, ſelf-exiſtent, and not ſelf-exiſtent, incarnate and not incarnate;</hi> is this his flat Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction? A very Smatterer in Logick would ſoon tell him, that however it be a Contradiction to ſay that ſuch <hi>oppoſite predica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes' poſſunt attribui eidem, ſecundum idem, ad idem, eodem modo, &amp; tempore,</hi> yet to ſay, they may be attributed to the ſame Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, provided it be not <hi>ſecundum idem,</hi> or <hi>ad idem, eodem modo,</hi> is no Contradiction at all, as is granted by all, and as may be evinced by thouſands of Inſtances; why then may not the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Eſſence, as it is with the perſonal Property of Father, be ſaid to be unbegotten, as it is with the perſonal Property of Son, be ſaid to be begotten, or conceived (and if he mean no more by his ſelf-exiſtent and not ſelf-exiſtent, then the Caſe is alike: But if he take them in a different Senſe, they will not be found to be the diſtinct Predicates of the divine Perſons) and ſo, why may not the ſame divine Eſſence, under a different Mode or perſonal Property, or as belov'd with a Love of infinite Delight and Complacency, be ſtill the ſame Eſſence, but neither as unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, nor as begotten, but as proceeding? And ſo in like manner, may not the divine Eſſence, as it is with the perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Property of the Son, be incarnate, yet the ſame di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Eſſence, as it is with the perſonal Property of Father and Holy Ghoſt be not incarnate? Is there any thing of Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction in all this? No Man that knows what a Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, unleſs a deceitful Sophiſter, who would impoſe on others his own Sophiſms, would aſſert it; when theſe contrary Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicates are predicated of the ſame Subject; not in one and the ſame reſpect, but under ſuch different Reſpects as that Subject hath to different Perſons. Are not theſe very Predicates, <hi>viz.</hi> to be begotten, and not begotten; to beget, and not to beget (to uſe a familiar Inſtance) in like manner, truly attributed to the Nature of <hi>Iſaac?</hi> Do we not truly ſay, that as it related to <hi>Abraham,</hi> it was begotten, but did not beget, and as it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to <hi>Jacob,</hi> that it did beget, but was not begotten.—As to what he adds, <hi>that there could not any Attributes or Modes,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56998:17"/> or anything that inheres in a Subſtance be begot, becauſe they cannot ſubſiſt by themſelves:</hi> How falſe this is, and contrary to all ſound Reaſon, may appear, even from phyſical Generations, which are no other than ſeveral progreſſive Motions from one eſſential Mode to another; for the Matter it ſelf is not genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but only the eſſential Mode or Form, which being edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced out of the Power of the Matter, does not ſubſiſt of it ſelf, but inheres in the Matter, by Vertue whereof the Compound itſelf is ſaid to be generated, as being ſpecificated by it. His Diſcourſe in the laſt §. of this Chapter, <hi>viz.</hi> 38. is as vain as the former, yea, it is ſuch as is grounded on a meer Sophiſm, <hi>viz.</hi> that there's no Diſtinction of Perſons in God, becauſe every Perſon is the divine Subſtance, which is three different ways the ſame, that is, three different ways one; whereas if he would have reaſoned fairly, he ſhould have ſaid, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Perſon is the divine Subſtance, as it three different ways the ſame or one; but then this Concluſion, as hath been ſhewn, being falſe, which ſhould be the Foundation of all that follows, the whole Superſtructure built on it, as his Multiplication without Addition, and his Subſtraction without Diminution, muſt fall with it, and ſo the Falſehood and Sophiſtry of his other Reaſoning would clearly have been detected as now it is, there being a vaſt Difference betwixt thoſe two ways and Modes of ſpeaking, <hi>viz. every Perſon is that divine Subſtance which is three different ways the ſame</hi> (which imports no more, than that it is that divine Subſtance which ſubſiſts in three Perſons, and which is common to three) <hi>which is a manifeſt Truth; and that every Perſon is the divine Subſtance Subſtance, as it is three different ways the ſame</hi> (which imports that every Perſon being the ſame with the divine Subſtance, as ſubſiſting in one way, as for example, with that Mode of Subſiſtance which is peculiar to the Son, is the ſame with that divine Subſtance, as ſubſiſting in another way, as for example, with that Mode of Subſiſtence which is peculiar to the Father) which is a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt Untruth: And ſo to father Contradictions on us, he'll ſpeak them himſelf, and then make us ſpeak them whether we will or no.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> Thus, having done with his third Chapter, we proceed to his Reflections on the Adimadverter's Hypotheſis, <hi>chap.</hi> 4.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:56998:18"/> 
               <hi>p.</hi> 12. where I ſhall briefly take notice of his trifling Diſcourſe, without taking on me to defend the Animadverter's Hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, which I have not ſeen, ſave only ſo far as to vindicate it, as here repreſented by the Author, from ſome unjuſt Aſperſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which he ſeeks to caſt upon it; and whereas, §. 39. he tells us, <hi>the common Opinion of the Trinitarians, even from the Beginning</hi> (if we may believe the Animadverter) <hi>has been, that the three Perſons are not three Subſtances, Attributes, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, or any real but incompleat Beings,</hi> viz. <hi>three Modes, and if the Perſons are no more than three Modes, then the Difference is but a trifling Difference.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But doth not this Author ſhamefully wrong the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverter, in making him ſay, that <hi>the three Perſons are no more than three Modes?</hi> Did ever any Trinicarian or Man of common Senſe talk at that rate? But as if he were afraid of being call'd to account for ſuch falſe Aſperſions, he tells us af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward in the ſame Section, <hi>viz. But it's ſaid, a Perſon is not a meer Mode, but the divine Subſtance with a peculiar Mode.</hi> It's well he's brought at laſt to make a true Repreſentation of the Trinitarians Doctrine, and thereby to confute his own Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny: And what hath he now to ſay againſt this, that a Perſon is not a meer Mode, but the divine Subſtance, with a peculiar Mode? He ſaith, <hi>that if each Perſon is the divine Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, he muſt have in him all the Modes;</hi> an admirable Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, <hi>If Perſon be divine Subſtance with one Mode, then he's di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Subſtance, as with all Modes.</hi> If this be not to ſpeak Contradictions, I know not what is; but he would back his abſurd Inference with a Reaſon, <hi>That Perſon muſt have all the Modes, becauſe he is the divine Subſtance in which the Modes ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt;</hi> this Reaſon is juſt like the former, as if Perſon, who is the divine Subſtance, as limited with one Mode or relative Property, is the divine Subſtance, not as limited with one, but three relative Modes or Properties: A downright Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction. One ſhould think this Man, who is ſo ready to charge others with flat Contradictions, ſhould better have ſenced himſelf againſt venting Contradictions at this rate; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I paſs on, I would take notice of another Paſſage of his in this Section, not much ſhort of the former for Abſurdity,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56998:18"/> wherein, ſpeaking of theſe relative Modes, he ſaith, <hi>two of which may be abſent without the leaſt Alteration in the divine Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance or Properties:</hi> He might as well have ſaid, that where there is the Foundation of Sonſhip, yet the relative Property of Son doth not reſult or flow from it; which, according to the Senſe of all Mankind, is impoſſible.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> What the Author ſaith, §. 40. I ſhall take up when I come to the following Chapter, and ſo ſhall next conſider what he ſaith, §. 41. where he reaſons thus. <hi>If there be any Thought, Word, or any of thoſe Actions that are proper to intelligent Beings, that belongs to the one and not to the other, it ſhews that they are more than diſtinct Modes, they are diſtinct intelligent ſubſtantial Beings; and are not the Father and Son in Scripture frequently op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to one another, as intelligent Beings? The Father's knowing and loving the Son, is not the Son's knowing and loving the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but each has a numerical diſtinct Knowledge, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, diſtinct Eſſence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The whole of this his reaſoning is idle and perverſe like the former, and is grounded on either a groſly ignorant, or a wilful Miſtake of the Trinitarians Doctrine: The divine Acts or Operations, according to theſe, are either <hi>ad intra</hi> or <hi>ad extra;</hi> the Author's Diſcourſe, in the Beginning of the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Chapter, relates to thoſe <hi>ad extra,</hi> where we ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider them; but his Diſcourſe here, to thoſe <hi>ad intra,</hi> as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's knowing and loving the Son, the Son's knowing and loving the Father: Now theſe are acts of the divine Nature or Eſſence as reflecting on it ſelf, and lay the Foundations of rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Properties never to be altered, becauſe from theſe acts and their terms the perſonal Properties reſult, as hath been ſhewn before; therefore, according to his Doctrine, theſe internal acts, are in Nature before the perſonal Properties, or Perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity: And yet (according to Scripture Phraſe) they are attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to each Perſon with reſpect to another, in as much as each Perſon hath the divine Eſſence, with its Acts and Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, under a relative Mode appropriated to him; and ſo the Father is ſaid to love the Son, and the Son to love the Father: How, I pray? What, as this Author would have it, with two acts of Love really and numerically diſtinct, and theſe as flowing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:56998:19"/> either from two meer Modes, or if not ſo, from two really and numerically diſtinct Eſſences? How abſurd is all this, when it's evident to any Smatterer in Theology, that the internal acts thenſelves are of the divine Eſſence, and only their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction from relative Modes; ſo that there's no need either of more numerically diſtinct Eſſences for Performance of theſe acts, or to have them attributed to meer Modes, or to have the divine Perſon ungodded, and their true Subject deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as this Author does vainly and idly pretend. What he adds, § 42. is to no more purpoſe, unleſs he could prove that we make the divine Acts, Titles, Attributes, of one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon really diſtinct from the Acts, Titles, Attributes, of another, which he can never do. The Author, in his following §. <hi>viz.</hi> 43. would make the World believe that the Orthodox were forced to this way of explicating themſelves about the Trinity, becauſe they had no other way to keep up the Face of a Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and avoid profeſſing the apparent Tritheiſm of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Fathers, who held the Three Almighty ſubſtantial Perſons, were no otherwiſe one God, than becauſe they had the ſame common Nature, even as Three Men having the ſame Humane Nature, are but one Man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Not to mention here the old falſe Trick of ſeeking from the multiplying of Perſons in God to multiply Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Almighties: As to that open Tritheiſm of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Fathers, as holding the Three Perſons, no otherwiſe one God, than as Three Men partaking of one common Humane Nature, are one Man, it is ſuch an impudent ſhameleſs Calumny, that it can deſerve no other Anſwer, than to have the Brand of a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Lye ſet upon it; ſuch a falſe and blaſphemous Notion, as that God ſhould be a <hi>Genus</hi> to more divine Perſons, ſo as Man is a <hi>Genus</hi> to ſingular Men, I know not whether it ever en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the Heart of any; but that it ſhould be the Notion of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Fathers, and entertain'd by them, is ſo expreſly contrary to their Canons, and the Orthodox Doctrine of the Fathers at that time, that it needs no further Confutation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> As to what is added by the Author, §. 44. (beſides his Reproaches which will light on himſelf) there's nothing but what we have had before over and over, and hath been ſo
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:56998:19"/> fully anſwered, in our having ſhewn that the glorious Almith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Being, doth not propagate Perſonality, by Termination of Extenſion, ſo as a finite rational Being doth, and that it's highly conſiſtent both with Scripture and Reaſon, and that he doth this by the aforeſaid reflex Acts, terminated on him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that no more needs be added here. But, §. 45. he tells us, <hi>that granting there are never ſo many Modes, yet if each Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon has the divine Subſtance, he muſt neceſſarily have all the Modes, becauſe they are Modes of the divine Subſtance; each Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon has the divine Subſtance as limited by a peculiar Mode, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative Property, and therefore cannot poſſibly have all the Modes, quite contrary to what is abſurdly inferred by this Author.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I come now to Chapter 5. to weigh the Author's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections<note place="margin">On Ch. 5.</note> on the Hypotheſis of Dr. <hi>W. S.</hi> of the Author of the Trinity placed in its due Light, and the reſt of the Nominal Trinitarians.</p>
            <p>In this Chapter the Author tells us, that <hi>beſides the Abettors of this Opinion, there are a great many Trinitarians, who no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe differ from the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians but in Name, whoſe Trinities they not only allow, but contend for:</hi> ſome of them ſay (and Dr. <hi>Wallis</hi> hath writ in Defence of it) <hi>That the three Perſons are only three external Denominations of God, according to the three different Operations of his Goodneſs towards his Creatures, in cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating, redeeming, and ſanctifying them;</hi> a little after he ſaith, <hi>Others ſay, that the three Perſons are the ſame in God as Faculties in Man</hi> (viz.) <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, Will, and Memory: Others, that the three Perſons are the three Attributes of God, Power, Wiſdom and Goodneſs:</hi> Here you have his Charge. But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. I ſhall believe it to be a falſe Charge, ſo prone I find him to charge things on the Trinitarians, till ſuch time as he doth quote the Author, at leaſt his Book and Page where the Mattter charged is expreſly contained. (2.) Tho I rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily grant that thoſe three Denominations of Creator, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, Sanctifier, are three external Denominations of God, according to the different Operations of his Goodneſs towards his Creatures, in creating, redeeming, and ſanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them; yea, and that theſe three different Operations, <hi>Imo omnes operationes ad extra</hi> (according to Scripture, <hi>Joh. 13. chap.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:56998:20"/> chap.</hi> 5. 17. and the granted Maxim) <hi>ſunt trium perſonarum communes,</hi> yet withal I affirm, that in reſpect of the Order that is amongſt the three Perſons, the Holy Scriptures do in a more ſpecial manner appropriate the firſt kind of theſe Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as the Acts of Creation to God the Father, as firſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and thoſe which in Nature are next to theſe, as of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation and Redemption, to God the Son; and thoſe which come laſt in Order, as the ultimate compleating Acts, to God the Holy Ghoſt; and accordingly do appropriate the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Denominations of Creator, Redeemer, Sanctifyer, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting from the ſaid Acts. But that any Man of common Senſe holding the Doctrine of the Trinity, ſhould affirm, that the Three Perſons are only three external Denominations of God, according to his ſaid different Operations, I am far from believing. (3.) Tho I grant, that ſome, who aſſert a Trinity of Perſons in God, may tell us, that theſe Three glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Perſons in God, are repreſented by thoſe three Faculties in Man, <hi>viz.</hi> Underſtanding, Will, and Memory, or theſe three Attributes of God, Power, Wiſdom, and Goodneſs, but that theſe ſhould ſay, that the Three Perſons are the ſame as Faculties in Man, <hi>viz.</hi> Underſtanding, Will, and Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; or that they are thoſe three Attributes of God, Power, Wiſdom, and Goodneſs, I cannot believe; but ſhall rather account, that he ſaith (till he make it good) a meer Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. And now being ſo perſwaded as I am, I might juſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt from giving my ſelf any further Trouble in this Place, ſave for ſome few Paſſages in this Chapter, which I may not whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſs over: One is in §. 46. A Queſtion grounded on his own falſe Hypotheſis (<hi>viz.</hi>) of there being no other Trinity but of infinite Goodneſs, Wiſdom, and Power, in one divine Being; Hence he puts the Queſtion, <hi>Is it not Idolatry to pay divine Worſhip to three Beings, each of which (ſince each is God) has in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Wiſdom, Power, and Goodneſs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's granted, that to pay divine Worſhip to Three Beings, whatever Attributes we cloath them with, is Idolatry; but to pay divine Worſhip to Three glorious Perſons, Father, Son, and Spirit, who are one and the ſame divine Being, and ſo
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56998:20"/> equally ſhare in all the glorious Attributes, and infinite Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of that Being, is that true Worſhip, which the Holy Scriptures, and the infallibly inſpired Pen-men of it, have preſcribed to us; and to call this Idolatry, is the higheſt Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, tending to overthrow the very Foundations of the Chriſtian Religion, and of the Chriſtian Faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But this Author propounds another Queſtion, <hi>viz. If there be but one Being with infinite <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>underſtanding, is it not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful to adore three ſuch Beings, each of which has an unlimited <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If this Author had propounded this Queſtion to Dr. <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock,</hi> or ſome, whom he ſtiles real Trinitarians, he might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps have had ſome Grounds for it; but to propound it to thoſe, with whom he hath to do in this Place (when he knows they grant as fully as himſelf, or any Unitarian can do, that it's unlawful to adore Three Beings, each of which has an unlimited Underſtanding) is not only a frivolous idle Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but on his part very malicious, as importing that thoſe, whom he ſtiles nominal Trinitarians, do this, when he knows the contrary; that he knows the contrary, is evident from his own fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Words, wherein he tells us, <hi>that the Trinitarians are really as zealous as they pretend to be, to defend the ſacred Truth of only one divine Being:</hi> Well then, if theſe Trinitarians be zealous Aſſerters of only one divine Being, as well as his Unitarians, how comes he to ask them, <hi>if it be not unlawful to adore three ſuch Beings?</hi> As if they did this, when he knows they abhor it. But this Author will tell us here,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object. 1. That it's not in Sincerity, but only in Pretence, that theſe Trinitarians ſeem zealous in Defence of one Being.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> If he could make the World believe, that theſe mean the ſame by Being, as they do by Perſon, which in this very Place he does cunningly, but moſt falſly inſinuate in his Jumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thoſe two Terms together, <hi>Being</hi> or <hi>Perſon,</hi> as if they were the ſame in the Language of Trinitarians as well as Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians: Then he might well perſwade, that their Zeal, for Defence of one Being, whilſt they aſſert Three Perſons in God, was but a pretended Zeal; But when he knows that all
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:56998:21"/> theſe do aſſert Three Perſons in God, yet but one Being, then what leſs can his charging theſe with want of Sincerity in their Defence of one Being, be, but meer Calumny? His other rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Language in this §. hath, for its Foundation, not the true Doctrine of the Trinitarians, but his own ignorant or wilful Miſtakes about that Doctrine. But, 2. I proceed to conſider, what this Author lays down i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the two laſt Sections of this Chapter, §. 47, 48. One while he repreſents theſe Trinitarians as ſuch, to whom the Unitarians owe their utmoſt Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment for vindicating their way of Worſhip, and for joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with them againſt the Politheiſts, and diſguiſed Pagans (as Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>) Another while as the ſame with Polytheiſts or diſguiſed Pagans, or as he means, with the real Trinitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. Again, he tells us, he knows not under what Head to rank theſe who will be thought to be neither real nor nominal Trinitarians; he thinks they believe no Trinity at all, that they are forced, in adoring the Trinity, to confeſs they adore an unconceivable Myſtery, which is only worſhiping of Words and Sounds, or a Trinity of Cyphers; that if they declare what the Three are, they muſt inevitably run into Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytheiſm or Unitarianiſm; that in ſaying the firſt of the Three is God the Father, the ſecond God the Son, the third is God the Spirit, they make them Three Gods, whom they equally adore: And <hi>p.</hi> 16. he aske what theſe Three are, <hi>Father, Son,</hi> and <hi>Spirit; Are they three Gods, three Parts of God, three Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, three Names?</hi> And concludes in a ſcoffing way, that it ſeems, <hi>the whole Myſtery of the Trinity lyeth in this, tho' every one can tell what each of the three is, yet none can tell what three they are, or how they are three.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee how this Author runs on in his old Cant, refuſing to take in any Satisfaction as to his Doubts and Queries abou the Trinity, which he might have done a thouſand times from the Writings of eminent Divines on this Subject, had he been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to be informed, or to have had his Doubts ſatisfied, as he pretends to be. For,</p>
            <p>1. Do they not tell him, that the Three, who bear Record in Heaven, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Word,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> are Three Perſons in one God-head? And does he not know
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:56998:21"/> that they ſay ſo? Why then does he propoſe thoſe idle Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Are they three Gods, three Parts of God, three Properties or Powers of God, three Names;</hi> and why does he bely them, when in Anſwer to that Queſtion, <hi>What Sort of three are they,</hi> He makes them ſay that's impoſſible to be known?</p>
            <p>2. Do they not tell him likewiſe, that theſe Three Perſons are one and the ſame great and bleſſed God, and yet diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from each other by perſonal Properties? that the firſt Perſon or Father is God, as limited with the perſonal Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of begetting or conceiving; that the ſecond is God, as li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited with the perſonal Property of being begotten; that the third is God, as limited with the perſonal Property of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from Father and Son, and of being ſent as Comforter; ſo that one Perſon cannot be another Perſon, and yet all the Three are one and the ſame bleſſed God?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 3. Let me add, Is it only theſe Divines that ſpeak thus, or is it not the divinely inſpired Pen-men of the Holy Scripture, who ſpeak the ſame? The Author of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> doth he not tell <hi>chap. 1. v.</hi> 3. That <hi>the Son is the expreſs Image of his Father's Perſon;</hi> and can he be a Son, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting as a lively Image, the Perſon of his Father, and yet not a diſtinct Perſon? Doth not St. <hi>John, chap.</hi> 1. expreſly tell us, <hi>that the Word was made Fleſh,</hi> and was this the Father, or the only begotten of the Father? See <hi>v. 14. This only begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of the Father,</hi> when in the Humane Nature he was bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, was he not a diſtinct Perſon from the Perſon of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, teſtifying of him by a Voice from Heaven, <hi>This is my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Son in whom I am well pleaſed?</hi> And was he not a diſtinct Perſon from the Holy Ghoſt, who deſcended in a bodily Shape like a Dove upon him? <hi>Luke</hi> 3. 21, 22. And does not our Lord Chriſt himſelf, when ſpeaking of Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, clearly diſtinguiſh theſe as Three Perſons, in tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us, <hi>John 14. 26. But the Comforter, which is the Holy Ghost, whom the Father will ſend in my Name, he ſhall teach you all things;</hi> have we not here the Perſon ſending, the Perſon ſent, and the Perſon in whoſe Name he's ſent? But what need I thus argue for a Diſtinction of Perſons? I don't at all queſtion here, but this Author will readily grant, that the Father, the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:56998:22"/> Word, and the Holy Ghoſt, as ſet forth in Scripture, are three different Perſons, for he tells us, P. 32. §. 94. <hi>It is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that in Scripture, God the Father is as much diſtinguiſh'd from the Son as two Men or Angels can be; and Mankind that are incapable of apprehending Metaphyſical Niceties, cannot but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them ſo;</hi> and hence it is (as we have ſhewn before) that he makes God and the Father, or Perſon of the Father, equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent Terms, ſo excluding the Son and bleſſed Spirit from being God, or equal to the Father, ſo that he owns them no otherwiſe to be Three Perſons, than as three Beings or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, which do really differ one from another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> You will thus ſee at length, what this Author is, and how his ſometimes ſeemingly applauded Unitarianiſm ends in Arianiſm; and the Truth is, the very worſt Dregs of the Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his Doctrine lye here, not in his denying any Trinity of Perſons, but his denying a Trinity of Perſons in the Unity of the divine Eſſence; he can be well enough content that the Word be the Perſon incarnate, the Holy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Ghoſt the Comforter, or Perſon ſent, ſo he can but ſtrip them of their Divinity, or make that Divinity, which the Scripture ſeems (as he grants) to aſcribe to them, to agree to them only in a tropical or figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative Senſe; but to aſcribe this truly to them, together with proper divine Worſhip, this he makes to be Idolatry. Here,</p>
            <p>1. I would have it noted (that I may meet with and refute his Railery, which hath diffuſed it ſelf through a great Part of his Pamphlet) that when this Author ſpeaks of the Trinitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an's worſhiping the Three Perſons, as Three diſtinct Almighty Beings, as Three Gods, as Three compleat diſtinct Objects of Worſhip, and as paying at other times divine Worſhip to one of them, and at the ſame time not paying it to another, that all this is meer Calumny, and hath not a Word of Truth in it; they worſhip indeed Three Perſons as they are one and the ſame Almighty Being or God, but not as Three Almighty Beings or Gods, ſuch Tritheiſm they abhor as much as himſelf or any other. They worſhip Three Perſons, what, as three diſtinct Objects of Worſhip? No, but as all three in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, making up the one great compleat and adequate Object of our Worſhip; they worſhip the Son and bleſſed
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:56998:22"/> Spirit as well as Father; but do they, when they worſhip the Son, not worſhip the Father and bleſſed Spirit at the ſame time? Or when they worſhip the bleſſed Spirit, do they not worſhip the Father and the Son at the ſame time, as this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor would Perſuade? That's falſe; yea, it's impoſſible that divine Worſhip ſhould be paid to one of theſe, and not to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, when the Three are but one and the ſame God, bleſſed for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> Here I would ask this Author, when he does in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip apply himſelf to God as our great Redeemer, does he in his ſo doing exclude God our Creator from ſharing in that Worſhip? Or when he doth in a more ſpecial manner apply himſelf to God as our Sanctifier, doth he by ſo doing exclude God our Creator and Redeemer from ſharing in that Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtip? And muſt he, for this his applying himſelf unto God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe different Reſpects, needs be a Polytheiſt and an Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>later? If not, why then muſt Trinitarians be ſuch for applying themſelves in divine Worſhip to the Perſon of the Son, or of the bleſſed Spirit? If he ſay it is becauſe three divine Perſons are three Gods,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is moſt falſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> moſt repugnant to Deſcriptions given by all ſound Trinitarians of divine Perſons, and hath fully been anſwered, and therefore I ſhall here paſs it over as a meer Calumny.</p>
            <p>2. I would have it noted, that when the Author tells us, §. 47, <hi>that the Notions of the Trinitarians, when apply'd to the Incarnation and Satisfaction, must be very uncouth;</hi> and further, <hi>that when they ſpeak of theſe, and when they endeavour to prove the Spirit and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to be Perſons, that then they are real Trinitarians; that is, ſuch (in his Language) as ſet up three Gods;</hi> and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther adds, §. 48. <hi>that theſe, who will be thought to be neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al nor nominal Trinitarians, cannot properly be ſaid to believe any Trinity, except at the moſt a Trinity of Cyphers, and that</hi> (as he thinks) <hi>it cannot be preſumed that Men of ſo great Senſe (to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion no other than</hi> Sarum <hi>and</hi> Worceſter) <hi>would aſſert ſo abſurd a thing, but that they knew, if they declared what they ſuppoſe the three to be, they muſt inevitably run into Polytheiſm or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitaria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:56998:23"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. And is there then no Medium betwixt theſe two Extreams? One would have thought that the Writings of ſo many learned Men as have writ on this Subject, if he had not reſolved to have ſhut his Eyes againſt cleareſt Light, ſhould have convinced him that there is. Do not theſe expreſly tell (if we muſt repeat things again) that theſe three are three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; that however three Perſons cannot exiſt in one ſingular finite Eſſence, where Perſonality flows from the Termination of Eſſence, yet three Perſons may exiſt in one ſingular, infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, immenſe Eſſence, where Perſonality flows from Eſſence after a different manner (which the boldeſt <hi>Arians</hi> and <hi>Sacini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> dare not deny.) And if Perſonality does not reſult from divine Eſſence, as it does from created Eſſence, why there may not exiſt three Perſons in the one, when yet there can but one exiſt in the other, it's neither this Author nor any other Man living (how big ſoever theſe may ſwell with Pride) that can ſhew any ſolid Reaſon to the contrary; and when once divine Revelation hath aſſured us it is ſo, who is this Man that dare fight againſt God? Will he tell us, that he hath been in Heaven, or beheld from all Eternity, what God, by eternal Acts, terminated on himſelf, can do or not do? To hear a vile Worm ſo talk as he doth, what horrid Boldneſs is it? Were I minded to do it, I could eaſily inſtance in ſeveral things about the divine Attributes, as difficult to be explicated and fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved as any he can propoſe to Trinitarians about the Exiſtence of three Perſons in the God-head, and what then muſt we, becauſe of this, call thoſe divine Attributes into Queſtion? And rather not cry out with the great Apoſtle, <hi>Oh the Depth!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. How uncouth then muſt the Notions of theſe Trinitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans be, when applyed to the Incarnation and Satisfaction, or to the Spirit or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as Perſons? Ichallenge him or any of his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, how highly ſoever pretending to Reaſon, to ſhew the Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtency of theſe Notions, when ſo applyed, with true and right Reaſon; or that any ſuch thing as Polytheiſm (as he vainly pretends) can be inſerred from them. Indeed, if one ſhould grant him, that one ſo often begged abſurd Principle of his <hi>(viz.) That if God the Son be the ſame God with the Father, then he muſt be the ſame Perſon with the Father; or if he be God,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:56998:23"/> and yet a diſtinct Perſon, that he must be a diſtinct God;</hi> Then it were no wonder, if <hi>uno abſurdo conceſſo mille ſequerentur.</hi> But when he's told by Trinitarians a thouſand times over, <hi>that the Son, altho' he be the ſame God with the Father, or the ſame with the Father as to God-head, Nature, Eſſence, Subſtance, yet he's not the ſame with the Father as to perſonal Property; that, altho there be three different Perſonal Properties in one and the ſame God-head, yet that ſame God-head, as limited by one Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Property, cannot be the ſame, as limited by a different Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Property, that is, cannot be the ſame Perſon, however it be in it ſelf the ſame God head ſtill.</hi> And now I pray, why may not one and the ſame God-head or divine Eſſence, as it is with one perſonal Property, be not incarnate, as it is with another, be incarnate; as it is with one be unbegotten, as with another begotten; as it is with one, receive Satisfaction, as with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make Satisfaction; as it is with one ſend, as with another be ſent? He muſt be quicker ſighted than I, that can ſee any thing like a Contradiction here; as if contrary Predicates were here affirmed, <hi>de eodem, ſecundum idem, ad idem,</hi> &amp;c. when it's clear they are not: So that his loud Clamour, <hi>Chap. 6. P.</hi> 17. §. 50. That this Suppoſition, <hi>That</hi>
               <note place="margin">On Ch. 6. Of real Trinitarians. Note, here I ſhall not concern my ſelf with theſe, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, not with this or the Author's follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chapters, further ther than I find him inveighing againſt the Orthodox Trinitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</note> 
               <hi>each Perſon is the ſame God,</hi> carries with it an innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable Company of moſt obvious Contradictions, ſuch as he tells us he will inſtance in §. 50, 51. will be found to be but a meer empty Sound, without any thing of Senſe or Reaſon, and all his pretended moſt obvious Contradictions vaniſh into Smoak, as any Smatterer in Logick might eaſily ſhew him. That which hath been ſaid, might, I hope, ſatisfie a judicious Reader, and ſerve for Anſwer to ſuch fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cavils and blaſphemous Invectives as this Author hath, <hi>P.</hi> 24, 25, 26, 27. and <hi>P.</hi> 31. §. 93, 94. of his Letter, not ſo much againſt the Trinitarians, as againſt the ſacred Scriptures and the bleſſed God, Father, Son, and Spirit, as revealed in Scripture, but I fear his glorying, if I ſhould ſo much as ſeem to paſs them over. Therefore,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 1. As to what he ſaith, <hi>chap. 8. p. 24 §. 74. That none of the Trinitarians beſides the Author of the 38 Propoſitions, can ſay,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:56998:24"/> that any of their Perſons is a moſt perfect God, or a moſt high God, or the only true God, or ſupream God, becauſe there are two others as perfect, as high, as true,</hi> &amp;c. will be found to be very idle and trifling, if it be but conſidered, that each Perſon in the moſt bleſſed Trinity, is the moſt perfect, high, wiſe, ſupream God; becauſe the ſame moſt high God with the other two Perſons, and neither a diſtinct God from them, nor they diſtinct Gods from him, as this Author doth falſly ſuppoſe; and if each one be the ſame God with the other, then each muſt be the moſt perfect, high, true, ſupream God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 2. As to what he ſaith, §. 76. of the ſame Page, <hi>That Trinitarians do imagine, that when Man was made, there was a Conſult of the whole Trinity about that weighty Affair, and that one ſaid to the others, Let us make Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Author might do well to ſpeak out plainly, and tell us, that his Deſign is to quarrel not ſo much with Trinitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, as with the Holy Scriptures themſelves, for the Words he quotes to quarrel with, <hi>Let us make Man,</hi> &amp;c. whoſe Words are they? Are they the Words of any other Trinitarian, ſave of <hi>Moſes, Gen.</hi> 1. 26. the infallibly inſpired Penman of that Book, or rather of the bleſſed Spirit himſelf, as ſpeaking by <hi>Mojes?</hi> Our Divines, I confeſs, make uſe of this Scripture for proving a Plurality of Perſons in the Unity of the God-head, and it's a full and clear Scripture for that purpoſe; but I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not wonder at this Author, if after his bold Attempt of ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the bleſſed Spirit of his Divinity, he proceed to that Height of Blaſphemy, as to make him ſpeak falſly or ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly in Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 3. As to what he adds in the ſame § that according to the Trinitarians, <hi>the Son, as God, really wanted Glory, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Father,</hi> John 17. 5. <hi>to give it him,</hi> telling us (in a ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing way) <hi>it is ſtrange that a moſt high God ſhould want and beg of another to ſupply him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It's falſe, that the Trinitarians ſuppoſe, that the Son, as God, really wanted Glory; they do indeed ſuppoſe, that the Son, as God, being made Fleſh, or taking our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture on him, by his dwelling in a poor humane Nature, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the State of his Humiliation, had the Glory of his Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:56998:24"/> much obſcured and eclipſed, ſo that it did not ſhine forth with that Luſtre as before; otherwiſe the eſſential Glory was ſtill the ſame, and there was no want as to this, but only as to its Manifeſtation, which may very well agree to the moſt high God, as this Author himſelf muſt be forced to grant, if he will grant ſuch a Variety of divine Providences towards the Sons of Men, as make his Glory to ſhine forth brightly at ſome times, but ſuffer it to be eclipſed and not manifeſted to theſe at other times. But,</p>
            <p>2. Seeing the Author would ſeem ſo quick-ſighted as to find an Argument in this Scripture, <hi>John</hi> 17. 5. againſt the Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Jeſus Chriſt, but ſo ſtark blind as to find none in the ſame Scripture for it; I would therefore improve it a little, for getting the Scales of his Blindneſs removed; and whereas our Lord Chriſt prays, <hi>Glorify me with thine own ſelf, with that Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry which I had with thee before the World was:</hi> Hence I argue; if the Glory that Chriſt the Son had with the Father before the World was, was not the increated Glory of the Son as moſt high God (which this Author does ridicule) then it was but the Glory of a created Being. But that could not be: For,</p>
            <p>1. If it was but the Glory of a created Being, then there was a created Being, before Creation, yea, before the firſt Moment of Creation: But that's impoſſible, and the Author himſelf who is ſo good in finding out Contradiction (where there's none) will ſure ſee a Contradiction in this.</p>
            <p>The Conſequence is undeniable, for the very firſt Moment of Creation God gave Being or Exiſtence to the Heaven and Earth, as the Phraſe in <hi>Gen.</hi> 11. clearly imports, and yet the Son had his Glory with the Father before this, (<hi>i. e.</hi>) through the boundleſs Tracts of Eternity. Let the Author anſwer this Argument if he can. But (2.) If the Glory which the Son had with the Father before the World, was no other than of a created Being, then it highly concerns this Author to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare what created Being he means; for (1.) it could not be that of his Humane created Being, for Chriſt had no ſuch Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before he was born of the Virgin <hi>Mary:</hi> If then the Glory which the Son had with the Father, before the World was, was the Glory of ſuch Being, it muſt then be the Glory of ſuch
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:56998:25"/> Being, when there was no ſuch Being<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if this be not down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Contradiction, I know not what is.</p>
            <p>2. It could not be the Glory of Angelick created Nature, for Scripture is expreſs, that Chriſt took not on him the Nature of Angels, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 16. Beſides, Scripture ſets him above all Angels, making him the Object of their Worſhip, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 6. yea, in the very ſame Place, where it mentions them as miniſtring created Spirits, it mentions the Son as God having an eternal Throne, and as the great unchangeable Creator of this great World, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 7, 8, 10, 11, 12. Now if the Son did exiſt before the World, and yet neither as God, Angel, or Man, I wonder what Species of Beings this Author will reduce him to: He who in Scorn ſo often asks the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians what a ſomething they mean by a ſecond or third Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the Trinity; may well be asked what a ſomething he means by the Son of God, as having Glory with his Father be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the World was, and what a Compound he will make the Perſon of our Redeemer, as conſiſting of an Humane Nature, and of ſome other (yet never before heard of) pre-exiſting Nature? I doubt, before he have done, he'll turn that great Myſtery of God, manifeſted in the Fleſh, into a meer Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maera; but I tremble to mention ſuch Blaſphemies.</p>
            <p>4. As to what this Author adds, <hi>P.</hi> 25, 26, 27. of his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, §. 77, 78, 79, 80, 81, 82, 83. tho I find little beſides idle Repetitions of former Matter which hath already been fully anſwered; yet ſome few Remarks I ſhall make, and 1. Whereas he tells us, <hi>P. 25. That it is impoſſible that the ſame numerical Act of Creation could be done by three Perſons, becauſe the ſelf ſame Act could not be done three times, and if one Perſon does an Act, no other can do the ſelſ ſame. Anſw.</hi> Such Stuff as this and that which follows, argues the Author's groſs Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance about the divine Perſons, whom he ſuppoſeth to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate divided Beings like Humane Perſons acting <hi>diviſim &amp; ſeparatim;</hi> were this ſo, his arguing would be to purpoſe: But he knows well enough (and ſo his Ignorance will be found to be wilful Ignorance) that the Three Divine Perſons, according to the Doctrine of all Orthodox Trinitarians, are not divided Beings, Minds, Natures, Eſſences, but one and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ame moſt pure and ſimple divine Beings, Minds, Natures, Eſſences,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:56998:25"/> with three diſtinct relative Properties, which do not ſo much as make any real Compoſition in that one glorious Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and yet are true Relations ariſing from their proper Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations in that one moſt ſimple immenſe Being, as he may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily underſtand, from what hath been ſaid, if he have a Mind to be informed; and ſo he might have ſatisfied himſelf, that it contradicts no Idea of ours at all, that one divine Perſon does the very ſame numerical Action another does.</p>
            <p>2. Whereas in the ſame Page he does inſinuate, <hi>That infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Divine Wiſdom teacheth Men</hi> (he means according to the ſame Doctrine of the Trinitarians) <hi>that there are two needleſs and uſeleſs Perſons in God himſelf, whoſe Actions are to no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of purpoſe, only to do what the firſt Perſon is not only all ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to do, but actually and wholly does; that if the Son and Spirit muſt neceſſarily do the ſame Act, they are no other than neceſſary Agents, and all the Power muſt be in him with whom they cannot help doing the ſame Acts he wholly does. Anſw.</hi> This whole Diſcourſe is falſe and impious, and not without greateſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny fixed on Orthodox Trinitarians. For may he not find (if he will but take notice of it) generally averring,</p>
            <p>1. That the Second and Third Perſons are ſo far from being needleſs and uſeleſs, that they do as neceſſarily ſubſiſt in the divine Eſſence as the firſt Perſon? 2. That altho the Father has a free Will and Power to do or not do (<hi>viz. ad extra</hi>) whatever he pleaſeth, yet this muſt be ſo underſtood, that he hath this in Union and Conjunction with the Son and Spirit, and not as divided or ſeparated from them? Therefore, what he would infer, that the Son and Spirit muſt neceſſarily do the ſame Act the Father doth; conſequently, that they are no other than neceſſary Agents; that all the Power muſt be in him, with whom they cannot help doing what he wholly does; is idle and blaſphemous, as if the Power of doing, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Will for doing, were the ſole Power and Will of the Father, and not the joint Power and Will of Father, Son, and Spirit; or as if the Son and Spirit did not in entire Conjunction with the Father perform the ſame Act <hi>ad extra,</hi> and with the ſame Freedom, when the Act is the Joynt Act of all Three? And I pray, is that we ſay here the Language only of ſome late Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:56998:26"/> and not the Language of ſacred Scriptures, yea, and of Chriſt himſelf? What elſe do thoſe Words of our Lord im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, <hi>John 5. 17. My Father worketh hitherto, and I work,</hi> did not the Father work Miracles? Did not Chriſt work the ſame in Conjunction with him? And does not that Scripture, <hi>John</hi> 1. 1, 2, 3, 14. expreſly affirm, <hi>that the Word (ſtiled the only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of the Father) was in the Beginning, was with God, was God, the great Creator and Maker of all things, that without him was not any thing made that was made?</hi> It's a Wonder this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, when he reads ſuch a Scripture as this, can forbear for to caſt forth Reproaches on the divinely inſpired Evangeliſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf? for could any Trinitarian have, with greater Evidence ſet forth, That, 1. this Word was from the Beginning, and before the Beginning of all created Beings, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from Eternity? 2. That in this Beginning he was with God, and therefore a diſtinct Perſon from God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? 3. That he was God, <hi>viz.</hi> the ſame bleſſed God with the Father as to Eſſence? 4. That all things were made by him, and that without him was not any thing made that was made, that therefore the Father did make nothing but in Conjunction with the Word or Son, not in Separation from him, as this Author would have it? And as nothing that was made, was made without this Word, ſo this Word himſelf was not made, except he make himſelf, but is the eternal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created Being: Let this Author ſhew now if he can, what he hath to charge Trinitarians with, which he may not as well charge on this bleſſed Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But this Author is ſo far from granting the Concurrence of the Son or Spirit to the doing of the ſame Actions with the Father, notwithſtanding Scripture does moſt clearly teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie it (as in the Texts before cited) that he does boldly aver, <hi>That this is apparently falſe, the Scripture being f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll of Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, eſpecially thoſe they do to one another, as one being ſent by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, their going from, and returning to one another, which is impoſſible to ſuppoſe they all equally concurr'd in;</hi> a little after he adds, <hi>That they</hi> (viz. <hi>Trinitarians) cannot deny, but Father, Son, and Spirit act ſeparately</hi> ad extra, <hi>even with reſpect to the Creatures;</hi> and to prove this, he asks, <hi>Did not God the Son take the Man Chriſt into his God-head, when neither of the other took
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:56998:26"/> him into theirs, or were limited to him?</hi> He further adds,—<hi>They are ſo far from being one in a natural Senſe, that there is not ſo much as a moral <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion between them; they have different Wills and Inclinations; for inſtance, the firſt Perſon will not forgive Mankind, without having Satisfaction given him by a divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, nay, they ſay his Juſtice could not be ſatisfied without it; the Son is ſo far from being of the ſame Mind, that he freely offer'd himſelf, to ſuffer to appeaſe the Wrath of the firſt Perſon, and ſtill intercedes to the Father. The third Perſon neither gives nor receives Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. I know no divine Actions, <hi>ad extra,</hi> which are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in Scripture, whether in a proper and literal, or in a tropical and improper Senſe, but they may well enough agree to Father, Son, and Spirit, and they may equally concur in them: It's true, our Lord ſaith, <hi>Joh. 16. 25. I came forth from the Father, and am come into the World.</hi> Again, <hi>I leave the World, and go to the Father:</hi> But theſe Words do import no more, than that the Word being made Fleſh, and dwelling in that Humane Tabernacle, did for ſuch time as that Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was upon the Earth, manifeſt the divine Glory in it, and ſo his leaving the World, and going to the Father, imports no more than his ceaſing from ſuch a Way for Manifeſtation of the divine Glory, and from thenceforth reſerving ſuch Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation for Heaven, ſtiled God's Throne; ſo this makes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all to the Author's purpoſe, only imports God's mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Perſon of the Son, Manifeſtations of his Glory after different ways, ſometimes in the Humane Nature on Earth, which is his Footſtool, ſometimes in Heaven, which is his Throne; ſo <hi>Joh.</hi> 14. 26. our Lord ſaith, <hi>but the Comforter, which is the Holy Ghost, whom the Father will ſend in my Name, he ſhall teach you all things:</hi> What Action is there, the Words being rightly underſtood, wherein one Perſon may not concur as well as another? If the Author ſay, the Father's ſending the Spirit to teach the Church, is ſuch an Action: I anſwer, The Father's ſending here imports no more than the Father's wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that the Church be taught, and illuminated by the bleſſed Spirit; this being a Benefit which Chriſt hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed for it, and this teaching, ſuch as in reſpect of Order in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:56998:27"/> operating, is more eſpecially appropriated to the Third Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; but dare this Author therefore ſay, that the Father does therefore exclude himſelf, either from willing, that the Church be taught, or from teaching it himſelf, when the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Church all things, is ſuch a peculiar Work of God, that as it does infallibly evidence the true Divinity of the Holy Spirit, ſo the joynt Concurrence of Father, Son, and Spirit, in it: So we ſee the grand Arguments of this Author againſt the Trinity, which he thinks to be invincible, are no other than ſuch as do ariſe from his own Miſunderſtanding or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting the Senſe of Holy Scriptures. 2 As to that Query of his, wherewith he thinks doubtleſs to ſilence all Trinitarians, <hi>viz. Did not God the Son take the Man Christ into his God-head, when neither of the others took him into their's, or were united to him? Anſw.</hi> The Author in this, labours under a double groſs Miſtake of the Doctrine, both of ſacred Scripture, and of Trinitarians.</p>
            <p>1. In his confounding God-head with Perſonality: For doubtleſs the Humane Nature of Chriſt is truly united to that God-head which is common to the Three Perſons; as <hi>divina chariſmatum communicatis,</hi> and as that Name, <hi>Immanuel,</hi> God with us, or God in our Nature, do clearly import: And as that Scripture, <hi>Act. 20. 28. To feed the Church of God, which he hath purchaſed with his own Blood,</hi> does evince; tho at the ſame time, it be but united to the Perſonality of one of theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> the Son, and (through the Contrivement of eternal Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom) be made to ſubſiſt wholly, <hi>Subſtantiâ <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> or in the God-head, as limited by perſonal Property, that ſo this glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> might become a meet Repreſentative or Sponſor for us.</p>
            <p>2. Tho it be granted (for the Reaſon aforeſaid) that only the Perſon of the Son, did take the Human Nature into his Subſiſtence; yet this imports no more than paſſive Reception of that Humane Nature into his Subſiſtence, which was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded or united to it by the real joynt Action of the Three bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Perſons, and wherein they did equally concur, like as they do in other Actions relating to the Humane Nature, See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. 10. compared with <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 24. Yea, do act joyntly, as well
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:56998:27"/> in preparing a Body or Humane Nature, for the Perſon of the Son (compare <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 5. with <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 35.) as they do in uniting that Perſon with the Humane Nature, <hi>John 1. 14. The Word was made Fleſh.</hi> So that you ſee from the undoubted Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the Word, into what a ſecond groſs Miſtake this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor is fallen, when he affirms, <hi>that the Three Perſons do act ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, ad extra,</hi> as I have now made appear in that very In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance by himſelf, given of the Son's Incarnation.</p>
            <p>3. As to what is further objected by him, <hi>viz. That theſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are ſo far from being one in a Natural Senſe, that there is not ſo much as a Moral <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion between them, that they have different Wills,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Anſw.</hi> This whole Diſcourſe, upon due Search, will be found to be falſe and idle; for whereas he tells us, <hi>that the firſt Perſon,</hi> viz. (<hi>according to Trinitarians) will not forgive Mankind, without having Satisfaction given him by a divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and that his Juſtice could not be ſatisfied without it, when yet the Juſtice of the Second Perſon can be ſatisfied without it.</hi> How falſe is this? Where will he find any ſuch Trinitarians as ſay, <hi>That the Juſtice of the Second Perſon can any more be ſatisfied than the Juſtice of the Firſt without Satisfaction?</hi> nay, do they not tell him, that the Juſtice of the Firſt and Second Perſon is one and the ſame Juſtice? Should they talk as he makes them, they would be as ridiculous as he could wiſh them. I muſt tell him therefore, that the Act of being offended with the Sins of Mankind, as well as the Works of Creation and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, may as truly be attributed to one as to another Perſon, and alike to all; notwithſtanding that in reſpect of Order, in operating, ſome of theſe are more frequently at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to one, and ſome to another: Nor do we matter for his bold and impudent Scoff, of the Perſons being a Committee of Gods, where ſometimes one is Preſident, and ſometimes another is in the Chair, and that accordingly things run in each of their Names, being well aſſured, that the one great and bleſſed God ſubſiſting according to his infinite Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in Three Perſons, <hi>viz.</hi> as Father, Son, and Spirit, may and doth (as Scripture teacheth) for the Manifeſtation of divine Order, in the Operations of the Three Perſons, and for the Conſolation of his People, appropriate in more ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:56998:28"/> manner, ſome of his great Works, <hi>ad extra,</hi> to himſelf as Father, ſome to himſelf as Son, ſome to himſelf as Spirit, tho all the Three do joyntly and equally concur in all, and this without giving the leaſt Colour for Polytheiſm, or Multiplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods. But he adds, <hi>That the Son,</hi> viz. (<hi>according to us) is ſo far from being of the ſame Mind with the Father in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring Satisfaction, that he freely offered himſelf to ſuffer, even to Death, to appeaſe the Wrath of the Firſt Perſon, and ſtill inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedes.—Anſw.</hi> We have ſhewn that the Son is of the ſame Mind with the Father, in requiring Satisfaction, and we ſhall now ſhew that he is of the ſame Mind, as to the giving of it; for when he comes to give Satisfaction, does he not expreſly tell us, <hi>Pſal. 40. 7, 8 Heb. 10. 7, 9, 10. I delight, or I come to do thy Will O God, yea, thy Law is within my Heart?</hi> Can any thing be more evident, than that it was the Father's Will, as well as Chriſt's that he ſhould make Satisfaction? And did Chriſt freely offer himſelf to ſuffer even unto Death, before the Hands and Counſel of God the Creator of Heaven and Earth had determined this way of Satisfaction by the Death of Chriſt? See what Scripture ſaith, <hi>Acts</hi> 4. 24, 25, 26, 27, 28. And do not all ſound Trinitarians ſay the ſame? But this Author ſhould conſider what Trinitarians tell him, that our Lord Chriſt hath an Humane as well as a Divine Nature; that to ſuffer Death and to intercede, are Idioms of the Humane Nature, and muſt not be attributed to the divine Nature of the Son, and therefore he ſhould be cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious how he fathers his own falſe Notions on theſe. And what if Trinitarians ſet forth God as offended with fallen Man, by the Perſon of the Father; God as willing to recover and redeem ſaln Man, by the Perſon of the Son, for Reaſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned? Muſt therefore God the Father and Son have different Sentiments about Man's Fall, different Minds and Wills about Satisfaction and Redemption? Nothing more falſe; I hope it's cleared fully, that the Three Perſons in theſe, as in all other real Acts, <hi>ad extra,</hi> do joyntly and equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concur</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But it's yet hoped, by this Author, that he can baffle Trinitarians by their own Conceſſions: <hi>For do not theſe grant</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>That opera Trinitatis ad intra ſunt diviſa?</hi> And he
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:56998:28"/> does inſtance in the Father's Act of Generation, whereby he gave Being to Son and Spirit, wherein they did not, nor could not act, <hi>And what greater Argument</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>can there be that they are ſeparate Gods, than that they act ſeparately?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Suppoſe that Maxim, <hi>Opera Trinitatis ad intraſunt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſa,</hi> ſuch, that taken in a right Senſe, it may be granted; yet that wicked Concluſion he would draw from it, That the Three Perſons act ſeparately, and ſo are ſeparate Gods, does no way follow from it; which himſelf, if he would but weigh the Matter well, would be forced to acknowledge; for what if theſe Acts be divided, this (in a ſound Senſe) im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports no more, than that the Divine Eſſence, by its two great Faculties of Intellect and Will, doth exert thoſe two great Acts <hi>ad intra,</hi> one of eternal Intellection of its ſelf, another of eternal Dilection, which Acts yet are ſo divided, that neither the one can formally be ſaid to be the other, nor the Eſſence, as with the one, the Eſſence as with the other; nor the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence as with the Act, the Eſſence as terminating the Act; this is ſo clear, that no rational Man can deny it, and I queſtion not but the Author himſelf will acknowledge it: And yet, theſe Acts, tho thus divided, do not ſo much as imply (as he muſt needs confeſs) any real Compoſition in God, much leſs ſeparate Agents, or ſeparate Gods: Now, if we bring what hath been ſaid, to the Perſons in the Trinity, we ſhall find, that however theſe Acts, <hi>ad intra,</hi> abſolutely conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, be thoſe eſſential Properties or Perfections which are as communicable as the divine Eſſence it ſelf, yet if we conſider them as Foundations of relative perſonal Properties flowing and reſulting from theſe Acts, as for example, of that perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal relative Property of Generation (to inſtance in that which this Author doth inſtance in) and which Generation doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude both the foreſaid internal Act of the divine Eſſence, and alſo the relative Property of God the Father reſulting from it, and giving Denomination to it; then this Act, <hi>ad intra,</hi> ſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited by relative Property, is the peculiar Act of God as Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and not of God as Son or Holy Spirit; even as the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Eſſence it ſelf, abſolutely conſidered, is common to Three Perſon, but as limited by perſonal Property, is pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:56998:29"/> to one; and now I pray, where's our Author's ſeparate Agents, or ſeparate Gods, neceſſary for Performance of theſe Acts <hi>ad intra,</hi> when it's clear that theſe Acts, with the Terms of theſe Acts, are only diſtinguiſhed and divided as before, amongſt the Three Perſons by relative Properties; and where's that Polytheiſm or Multiplication of Gods, which he would ſo gladly charge on Trinitarians? Doth his arguing here flow genuinely from the Doctrine of Trinitarians, or only from the falſe Notions and Dreams of his own Brain? Is there any thing in all this Diſcourſe, affirmed of God, but what may be affirmed, and what himſelf cannot but affirm of every Angel, and of every Humane Soul; ſave with this Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that theſe Acts, <hi>ad intra,</hi> in the bleſſed God, being infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite and eſſential, are therefore generative and productive of Perſons in the God-head; when in Angels and Humane Souls, where they are but finite and accidental, they are not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductive in like manner: After all this, when it is ſo evident from divine Revelation (without which we ſhould for ever have been ſilent) that the Acts, <hi>ad intra,</hi> as they are in the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite eternal God, do differ in their Products, ſo as Trinita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians affirm from thoſe Acts, <hi>ad intra,</hi> which are but the Acts of finite Creatures, and when this ſtands in no real Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to Reaſon or the Light of Nature, but, tho tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to it, yet, when once revealed, is found to ſtand in ſweet Conſiſtency with it; I wonder what it is this Author would be at, unleſs it be, inſtead of ſubjecting himſelf to the written Word and divine Revelation, to take on him to be a Controu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, or rather ſcornful Gain-ſayer of it?</p>
            <p>As to his 79. §. we have ſhewn before, that Creation is the Work, tho of one glorious Being, yet as ſubſiſting in three Perſons; and here, tho we readily grant, that there is but one ſupream Preſerver and Governour of all things, yet we muſt tell, or rather let the Scripture tell him, That this ſupream Upholder and Governour of the World, is the great God, Father, Son, and Spirit; Son and bleſſed Spirit, joyntly and equally concurring with the Father in this great Work, and not the Father as ſeparated from them; for this ſee <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 3. Is not the Son expreſly ſaid here to uphold all things by the Word of his Power? Andis not the Saints new Birth, Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:56998:29"/> Inſtruction, or Direction, attributed to the Holy Spirit? Can any thing be more evident than that theſe glorious Perſons do act joyntly with the Father in the Preſervation of the Creatures, as well as in their Creation? How falſly then does he conclude, §. 80. <hi>That Creation, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, and ſupream Government of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe, demonſtrate that there is but one Divine Perſon?</hi> And that the ſame Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, in his ſaid §. 80. drawn from Adoration, Love, and Gratitude due to God, is as falſe as the former, I have fully before evidenced, <hi>P.</hi> 24. As to his 81. §. I muſt tell him, 1. That all ſound Trinitarians do acknowledge as fully as himſelf or any other, that there is but one divine Being or God, with a Power to know and do all things. 2. That the Heathens were without Excuſe for worſhipping ſeveral. 3. That for him to ſay, that theſe Trinitarians do pay divine Worſhip to more than one neceſſary ſpiritual Being, is a Charge ſo notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly falſe, that Satan himſelf could not have acted the Part of a more falſe Accuſer.</p>
            <p>But he tells us, §. 80. <hi>That it can no way allay our Crime to call them Perſons inſtead of Gods, ſince paying divine Worſhip to them does as much rob the only one of his due, as if we called them ſo many Gods. Anſw.</hi> Do we in worſhiping Three Perſons, rob the only one of his Due, when in expreſs Scripture Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5. 7. we profeſs that theſe Three are the only One, and the only One is theſe Three, <hi>viz.</hi> Father, Son, and Spirit? If in that Adoration we pay to the Son, and bleſſed Spirit, we ſhould pay it to them as ſeparated from the Father, excluding the Father from ſharing in it, he might have had ſome Colour for what he ſays; but when the Father is not excluded, but does equally ſhare in it; nay, when we do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that in all that Adoration we do direct to One of the Three, yet we as truly include all the Three, <hi>viz.</hi> Father, Son, and Spirit, as making up the only one compleat and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equate Object of Worſhip, the bleſſed God; even as he who does ſincerely direct his Worſhip to God as Redeemer, does yet truly include God our Creator and Sanctifier; will not his whole Charge be found to be falſe and blaſphemous Calumny? In his 82. §. he tells us, <hi>that not only <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians, but all Mankind that worſhip but one divine Being, are greatly
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:56998:30"/> ſcandalized at thoſe Chriſtians that pay divine Worſhip to ſeveral; and he beſeecheth theſe to let him underſtand how the Heathens, in their Devotions did or could do more to diſtinguiſh their divine Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, than theſe do by praying to each by himſelf, and terminating their Devotion on each? Anſw.</hi> If this Author have a Mind to be ſatisfied, I hope I have ſaid enough to ſatisfie him in this, and to let him ſee, that theſe Chriſtians are ſo far from imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Heathen in their idolatrous Worſhip of more Gods, that none but a Perſon groſly blinded with Heatheniſh Malice, taking almoſt everywhere his own ſilly and falſe Hypotheſes for granted Maxims, and inferring his Concluſions from ſuch Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, durſt have ventured to have charged them with it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But it is objected, <hi>Do we not in our Creed expreſly ſay, The Son is very God of very God? and how can we, after that, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend they are the ſame God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Well enough, for the Creed imports no more than that the Son is the very ſame God with the Father, tho as cloathed with a different relative Property through eternal Generation, he be God of God, in ſuch manner as is largely before declared.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But he tells us here, <hi>there are a hundred Actions which Scripture relates of one God, and denies of the other two Gods; as God the Spirit deſcending in a Bodily Shape, the Father and Son not deſcending.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1 Tho that Scripture, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. 16, 17. does ſignally evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence the Truth of Three Perſons, who in Chriſt's Baptiſm did differently repreſent themſelves, <hi>viz. Voce Pater, Natus corpore, flamen Ave,</hi> which made one of the Fathers ſay to one doubting of the Trinity, <hi>Abi ad Jordanem &amp; videbis;</hi> yet no ſuch thing as a Plurality of Gods, can be inferred from any Actions here performed. To mention that which himſelf does inſtance in, <hi>viz.</hi> God the Spirit's deſcending in a Bodily Shape; I ſuppoſe he muſt needs grant here, that Action of deſcending cannot be attributed to God in a proper Senſe, and therefore ſuppoſing the Spirit to be God, as Trinitarians ſay, can only be attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him in a tropical Senſe, ſuited to any manner of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, which is ordinary in Scripture; and whatever of Action
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:56998:30"/> it may import appropriated here to the Holy Spirit, yet it is but like all other Actions <hi>ad extra,</hi> common to the Three, as we have before fully evidenced, <hi>P.</hi> 30. where he may find what is here or elſewhere by him objected in reference to theſe Acts fully anſwered. But.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quest.</hi> 2. What then does this Author mean in telling of an hundred Actions which the Scripture relates of one God, and denies of the other two Gods? Does he charge Scripture and the divinely inſpired Penman of it with Polytheiſm, or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting a Plurality of Gods?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To do him Right, I think this is not his Meaning; but that by one God, he means the true God, and by the other two Gods, two made Gods, ſuch as truly are not God, but only have ſuch a Name, and are falſly advanced to divine Dignity by Trinitarians, whom therefore he charges as Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, yea, as bad or worſe than Pagans. More Stuff of like Nature he hath in his <hi>9th. Chapter,</hi> which, tho chiefly intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> and his Party, yet towards the Cloſe of it, as §. 93, 94. he does bitterly inveigh againſt the others as Polytheiſts and Idolaters, having a Creed not ſtuffed with ſo many Lines as Contradictions; yea, and when it's evident (as he tells us) that in Scripture God the Father is as much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from the Son, as two Men or Angels can be. In his 83. §. he adds, <hi>theſe things are ſo frequently objected, and ſo little Care taken to anſwer them be our Writers, that I thought I could not do better than to repreſent thoſe to you, that we may (if it be poſſible) receive a full and ſatisfactory Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I hope the Chriſtian Reader may fully ſee what this Author would be at; and I ſhould not thus far have raked into the filthy Dunghil of his Blaſphemies, but to make a full Diſcovery of him, and that even the weaker and more incau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Readers may now ſee him in his perfect Colours. For ſuch Concluſions as theſe are clearly deducible from his own Words, and the moſt candid Conſtruction that can be put on them. <hi>viz.</hi> 1. That God the Son, and God the Spirit, when worſhipped by Chriſtians with Divine Worſhip, become meer Idols. 2. That thoſe Chriſtians who adore theſe, or ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe, as true God, are as groſs Idolaters as Pagans,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:56998:31"/> who worſhip Stocks and Stones, and in ſome reſpects, more vile than they. 3. That all ſuch as write in Defence of a Trinity of Perſons, in the Unity of divine Eſſence, are ſimple Perſons, fond of venting abſurd and ſilly Hypotheſes, and Books and Creeds ſtuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d with nothing but flat Contradictions; and what I pray will follow from theſe Concluſions, but that, 1. All Chriſtians in the World, for many hundred Years together, were meer Idolaters, yea, as bad, or worſe than Pagan Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters? 2. That Idolatry deſtroying the very Eſſence of a true Church, Chriſt therefore, for about a thouſand Years, <hi>i. e.</hi> from the Time that Arianiſm was exploded by the Chriſtian World, till the time that it was broached anew by <hi>Socinus,</hi> had no true Church? Could any Pagan or Mahometan have diſgorged the Poyſon of a bitter Spirit againſt Chriſt and his Members, at an higher rate than this? But this Man pretends to believe Divine Revelation; let me then expoſtulate the Matter a little with him. Can he caſt all this Dirt on Trinita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, and not on Scripture and the ſacred Writers of it, yea, on Chriſt himſelf? Is it only Trinitarians that ſay, Chriſt is God equal with the Father; and doth not bleſſed <hi>Paul</hi> ſay the ſame, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 6? Is it theſe only that ſay, that we muſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the Son as we honour the Father, and doth not Chriſt himſelf ſay the very ſame, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 23? Do theſe only tell us that Chriſt the Son is the great Maker, Preſerver, and Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder of all things, and doth not the great Apoſtle St. <hi>John,</hi> in the firſt Chapter of his Goſpel, and <hi>Paul,</hi> in the firſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſay the very ſame? Is it theſe only that ſay, that the Son is the mighty eternal God, and doth not the great Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſay as much, Chap. 9. Verſ. 6. ſtiling him the mighty God, the everlaſting Father, or Father of Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? Or is it only theſe who pay that ſame Divine Worſhip to the Son, become our Redeemer, which they pay to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Conjunction with him, and do not the innumerable Companies of bleſſed Angels and Saints, yea, ten thouſand times ten thouſand of theſe, with every other Creature in his Kind, pay the very ſame? Let him conſult <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. 11, 12, 13. and he'll find they do; and muſt all theſe therefore be Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters? Oh Blaſphemy! And as to the bleſſed Spirit, is it only
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:56998:31"/> the late Trinitarians who acknowledge his Infinity and Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſcience, did not the Royal Prophet <hi>David</hi> do the ſame? See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139. 7, 8, &amp;c. Is it only theſe that declare him to be the true God, the great Searcher of Hearts, and did not the great Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> in the Caſe of <hi>Ananias,</hi> who lyed to the Holy Ghoſt, declare as much, when he told him, <hi>Act. 5. 3, 4. Thou haſt not lyed unto Men but unto God?</hi> And did not <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias</hi> to his Coſt find it ſo? The Author might do well to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, who it is he caſts his blaſphemous Reproaches on; were it only upon a Company of poor frail Men, who poſſibly may err, this were not ſo much, but to caſt theſe on ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, on the infallibly inſpired Pen-men of it, and on glorify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Angels, who ſay, and do as much as Trinitarians do; yea, and on Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, and on the Holy Spirit; this is dreadful. Before he had gone thus far, he might well have conſidered what our Lord ſaith, <hi>Mat. 12. 31. All manner of Sin and Blaſphemy ſhall be forgiven unto Men, but the Blaſphemy againſt the Holy Ghoſt ſhall not be forgiven unto Men;</hi> or, if it be not too late, I wiſh he might yet conſider it and repent. He pretends, §. 83. that his End in writing was to receive (if poſſible) a full and ſatisfactory Anſwer from thoſe learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Perſons, to whom he writes; and what if ſuch an Anſwer come from one, ſometimes Member of one of thoſe famous Univerſities, to whom he makes his Addreſs? Is not this as much as may ſuffice both for detecting and confuting his falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious arguing, and for giving ample Satisfaction, if he have an Heart prepared for Reception of it? However this be, thus much I can ſincerely profeſs, that for ſo much of his Letter as relates to thoſe Trinitarians, whom he doth abuſively ſtile No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal, and who indeed are the ſound and Orthodox Trinitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, I have been ſo far from overlooking any thing that might ſeem to have any Weight, or to carry any Colour of Reaſon with it, that I have choſen, rather as to ſome of his Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons repeated again and again in different Places, under ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what different Terms, to give Anſwer again and again, rather than ſuffer the incautious Reader to be deluded with them; only thus much I muſt mind the Reader of, that in the whole of this Diſcourſe, I have not medled at all with Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> or thoſe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:56998:32"/> of his Party who aſſert that the Perſons in the Trinity are Three diſtinct infinite Minds or Spirits, and Three individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Subſtances: And whom this Author ſtiles real Trinitarians: Theſe I confeſs have given too juſt Occaſion of Offence and Scandal to all ſober Chriſtians, who do not ſtand in need of ſuch Weapons for Defence of the Trinity againſt the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams, either of <hi>Arius</hi> on the one hand, or of <hi>Sabellius</hi> or the Unitarians on the other; for ſeeing, I find, theſe juſtly cenſured by thoſe learned and worthy Perſons—The Vice-Chancellor, and Heads of the Colleges and Halls in <hi>Oxford,</hi> in their Decree of <hi>Novemb. 25. A. D.</hi> 1695. I do fully acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſce therein. But as to the Author, with whom I have to do, when I came to that Part of his Letter, <hi>viz.</hi> Chap. 6, 7, 8, 9. which ſeems only to refer to theſe, and ſo had thought to have rid my Hands of him, yet peruſing theſe Chapters, I found ſo many things interwoven relating to the former, whoſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence I had undertaken (as if his Arrows were chiefly level<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at theſe) that I did plainly ſee, either I muſt do more, or leave this Author to glory, as if I had left ſome of his chief Arguments unanſwered; which now I hope he will not ſo much as pretend.</p>
            <p>And now I would ſhut up my whole Diſcourſe, but that his laſt Chapter about Myſtery, may call for theſe few brief Notes on it, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. That it argues intolerable Pride and Folly in him to prefer Reaſon as in fal'n Man, yea, his own magnifyed Ideas (of things which we have found already to be ſo falſe) to the moſt undoubted Traditions and Revelations of God in the Word, and to make thoſe the Rule and Touchſtone for trying theſe by, as it's clear he doth, §. 11.</p>
            <p>2. That it argues higheſt Impudence, and Impiety for him to make, as §. 103. 104. Myſtery, no mark of Chriſt or true Religion, but only of Antichriſt and Irreligion, when yet ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scripture tells him, 1 <hi>Tim. 3. 16. that great is the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Godlineſs, God manifeſt in the Fleſh,</hi> which clearly ſhews, that there's as well a Myſtery of Godlineſs relating to Chriſt, as a Myſtery of Iniquity relating to Antichriſt.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:56998:32"/>
            <p>3. Whereas he rails againſt the Myſtery of the Trinity as a cunningly deviſed Fable, for to keep People in Darkneſs, and make ſuch as were Children, be as Children ſtill, §. 95. I muſt tell him, this is no better than falſe and lying Slander; for he ſees how ready we are to enter the Liſt with him, and to vindicate our Doctrine both by Scripture and Reaſon from all his black Calumnies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 4. Whereas he pretends, that there's no Myſtery in Religion, as to the things themſelves, which are revealed, but only as to the manner of them (I ſuppoſe he means not as to their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) ſee his §. 96, 97, 98. and then tells us, that the Myſtery of the Trinity is a Myſtery as to the things themſelves, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſuch wherein we have no Ideas of the things at all, or but ſuch as are contradictory to the true, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain an Affirmation and Negation of the ſame thing; which he would more fully evidence §. 102. telling us, that to ſay, Three Perſons and one Perſon are the ſame God, is as great a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction as to ſay, Three Perſons and One are the ſame; and that we may as ſoon apprehend a Round Square, or a Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain without a Valley; which yet Trinitarians would maintain under Pretence of Myſtery; and this when not only Unitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, but all Mankind that worſhip but one Divine Being, are greatly ſcandalized at them for it is, as §. 82.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The whole of what is here objected, hath in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding Diſcourſe, been ſo fully anſwered; the Definitions of Perſon in general, and of divine Perſon, ſo clearly laid down; the Difference there is betwixt Subſtance, ſubſtantial Eſſence, and Perſon, ſo fully cleared; His pretended Contradictions (not reſulting from Trinitarian Doctrine (as he would have it (but from his own falſe Ideas about theſe things) ſo clearly refuted and confuted; that I would perſwade my ſelf, would he and thoſe of his Party betake themſelves to an impartial and unprejudiced Conſideration of what hath been ſaid, this, if it had no further Effect, yet would make both him and them for ever hereafter to deſiſt from theſe their loud and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Clamours againſt Chriſt's Church and faithful Servants; and make them grant, that theſe, by the true Doctrine of the Trinity, are ſo far from multiplying Gods, or Objects of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:56998:33"/> Worſhip, that they do not ſo much as attribute to our great and bleſſed God, any Properties, whether abſolute or rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, but what are revealed in the Word, and which being ſo revealed, Reaſon it ſelf, and the Light of Nature, muſt grant to be ſuch, as may flow from the Divine Eſſence, and its eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal intrinſick Acts, if the Perfection of theſe and their infinite Diſtance from finite Eſſence and Acts, be but duly known and conſidered.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:56998:33"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
